<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.discursive.com/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<appendix id="archiva">
  <title>Migrating to Nexus from Archiva</title>

  <section id="archiva-sect-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Apache Archiva</primary>

        <secondary>migrating from</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus plugin</primary>

        <secondary>Nexus Migration plugin</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

        <secondary>Apache Archiva</secondary>
      </indexterm>This appendix walks you through the process of migrating an
    existing Archiva installation to a new Nexus installation.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Migrating Archiva Repositories</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

        <secondary>migrating Archiva repositories</secondary>
      </indexterm>Archive uses the filesystem to store hosted repositories and
    proxied repositories, because of this migrating from Archiva to Nexus
    couldn't be simpler. The following sections outline the process for
    migrating existing Archiva repositories to a new Nexus instance.</para>

    <section id="sect-archiva-migrating-managed">
      <title>Migrating an Archiva Managed Repository</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

          <secondary>migrating Archiva managed repositories</secondary>
        </indexterm>Archiva Managed Repositories are the equivalent of Nexus
      Hosted repositories. To migrate a Managed Repository from Archiva to
      Nexus, all you need to do is:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create a New Hosted Repository in Nexus</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Copy the Contents of the Archiva Managed Repository to the
          Storage Directory of the newly-created Nexus Hosted
          Repository</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Rebuild the Index for the New Nexus Hosted Repository</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The following example will walk through the process of migrating
      the Archiva repository named "internal" to a new Nexus Hosted repository
      named "internal". To view your managed repositories in Archiva, login to
      Archiva as an administrative user and click on the "Repositories" link
      in the left-hand navigation menu. Clicking on "Repositories" will list
      all of your Archiva Managed repositories as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-archiva-managed" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-archiva-managed">
        <title>Archiva Managed Repositories</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/archiva-managed-repositories.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/archiva-managed-repositories.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>To migrate this Managed repository to a Nexus Hosted repository,
      you will need to find the directory in which Archiva stores all of the
      repository artifacts. to do this, click on the Edit link listed next to
      the name of the repository you want to migrate as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-archiva-managed" />. Click on Edit should load the form
      shown in <xref linkend="fig-archiva-managed-edit" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-archiva-managed-edit">
        <title>Editing an Archiva Managed Repository</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/archiva-managed-repo-edit.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/archiva-managed-repo-edit.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Take note of the file path for Directory. The file path shown in
      <xref linkend="fig-archiva-managed-edit" /> is
      <filename>./data/repositories/internal</filename>. If Archiva is
      installed in <filename>/usr/local/archiva-1.2.1</filename>, this would
      correspond to the directory
      <filename>/usr/local/archiva-1.2.1/data/repositories/internal</filename>.
      You will use this path later in this section to copy the contents of
      your old Archiva Managed Repository to your new Nexus Hosted
      Repository.</para>

      <para>Next, create a new Nexus repository with the same identifier and
      Name as the old Archiva Managed Repository. To do this, log into Nexus
      as an administrative user, click on Repositories in the left-hand Nexus
      navigation menu, and then click on the Add dropdown as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-archiva-new-nexus-hosted" />. Select "Hosted Repository"
      and then fill out the Repository ID and Repository Name to match the
      name of the old Archiva repository. If you are migrating a Snapshot
      repository, select a Repository Policy of Snapshot, and if you are
      migrating a Release repository select a Snapshot Policy of
      Release.</para>

      <figure id="fig-archiva-new-nexus-hosted">
        <title>Creating a Nexus Hosted Respository</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/archiva-new-nexus-hosted.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/archiva-new-nexus-hosted.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Now, you'll need to copy the Archiva repository to the Nexus
      repository. You can do this, by copying the contents of the Archiva
      repository directory to the Nexus repository storage directory. If we
      assume that Archiva is install in /usr/local/archiva-1.2.1, Nexus is
      install in /usr/local/nexus-1.3.6, and the Sonatype Work directory is
      /usr/local/sonatype-work. You can copy the contents of the Archiva
      managed repository to the new Nexus hosted repository by executing the
      following command:</para>

      <screen>$ <command>cp -r /usr/local/archiva-1.2.1/data/repositories/internal/* \
        /usr/local/sonatype-work/nexus/storage/internal/</command></screen>

      <para>If you are migrating to a Nexus instance which is on a different
      server, you can simply create an archive of the
      <filename>/usr/local/archiva-1.2.1/data/repositories/internal</filename>
      directory, copy it to the new server, and then uncompress your
      repository archive in the appropriate directory.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>Archiva stores artifacts from proxied remote repositories in the
        same directory as artifacts in a managed repository. If you have been
        proxying a remote repository, you might want to remove artifacts that
        have been proxied from a remote repository. For example, if your
        organization uses a groupId of <varname>org.company</varname> for
        internal project, you can make sure to only copy the artifacts under
        the corresponding <filename>org/company/</filename> directory.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>Once the contents of the repository have been copied to the Nexus
      Hosted repository, you must rebuild the repository index as shown in
      <xref linkend="figu-archiva-nx-hosted-idx" />. Right-clicking on the
      repository in the list of Nexus repositories will display the context
      menu shown in the following figure.</para>

      <figure id="figu-archiva-nx-hosted-idx">
        <title>Rebuilding the Index of a Nexus Hosted Repository</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/archiva-nx-hosted-rebuild-idx.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/archiva-nx-hosted-rebuild-idx.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Once the migration is complete, you will be able to search and
      browse the contents of your newly migrated Nexus Hosted
      repository.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Migrating an Archiva Proxy Connector</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

          <secondary>migrating Archiva proxy connectors</secondary>
        </indexterm>Archiva allows you to define remote repositories and
      repository connectors to proxy remote repositories and cache remote
      artifacts from remote repositories in Archiva Managed Repositories.
      While Nexus also provides Proxy repositories, there is one major
      difference between Nexus and Archiva. Where Nexus maintains a separate
      local storage directory for each proxy repository, Archiva combines
      cached remote artifacts into a single filesystem with the contents of a
      managed repository. In other words, there is no good way to transfer an
      existing local cache of artifacts between Archiva and Nexus without
      manually manipulating the contents of Archiva's Managed Repository
      directory.</para>

      <para>To recreate an Archiva repository connector in Nexus as a Proxy
      repository and to preserve the local cache of artifacts from this
      repository. You'll need to create a Proxy repository in Nexus, copy the
      contents of the existing proxy repository to the Nexus storage location
      for you new Proxy repository, and then rebuild the metadata of your new
      Nexus Proxy repository.</para>

      <para>First step is to take a look at the Remote Repositories in your
      Archiva installation: log in as an administrative user and then click on
      "Repositories" under the Administration menu in the left-hand Archiva
      navigation menu. Once you've clicked this link and loaded the list of
      repositories, scrool to the bottom of the page to see the list of remote
      repositories as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-archiva-browsing-remote" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-archiva-browsing-remote">
        <title>Browsing Archiva Remote Repositories</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/archiva-remote-repositories.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/archiva-remote-repositories.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Defining a proxy repository in Archiva involves associating one of
      the remote repositories defined in <xref
      linkend="fig-archiva-browsing-remote" /> with one of the Managed
      Repositories defined in <xref linkend="fig-archiva-managed" />. Once you
      do this, requests for artifacts from the managed repository will also
      query the remote repository. If an artifact is found in the remote
      repository, it will be retrieved and stored in the managed repository's
      storage directory. To see a list of proxy connectors and the managed
      repositories they are associated with, click on "Proxy Connectors" in
      the left-hand Archiva menu, you will see a list similar to that shown in
      <xref linkend="fig-archiva-proxy-connectors" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-archiva-proxy-connectors">
        <title>Archiva Proxy Connectors</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/archiva-proxy-connectors.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/archiva-proxy-connectors.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Click on the Edit Icon (or Pencil) next to second Proxy Connector
      listed in <xref linkend="fig-archiva-proxy-connectors" />, this will
      then load the settings form for this proxy connector shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-archiva-proxy-connector-settings" />. You should use the
      settings for this proxy connect to configure your new Nexus Proxy
      repository.</para>

      <figure id="fig-archiva-proxy-connector-settings">
        <title>Archiva Proxy Connector Settings</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/archiva-proxy-connector-settings.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/archiva-proxy-connector-settings.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>To create a Proxy repository that will correspond to the Proxy
      Connector in Archiva, log into Nexus as an administrative user, and
      click on Repositories in the left-hand Nexus menu. Once you can see a
      list of Nexus repositories, click on Add... and select Proxy Repository
      from the dropdown of repository types. In the New Proxy Repository form
      (shown in <xref linkend="fig-archiva-nx-create-proxy" />) populate the
      repository ID, repository Name, and use the remote URL that was
      displayed in <xref linkend="fig-archiva-browsing-remote" />. You will
      need to create a remote repository for every proxy connector that was
      defined in Archiva.</para>

      <figure id="fig-archiva-nx-create-proxy">
        <title>Creating a Nexus Proxy Repository</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/archiva-nx-proxy-create.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/archiva-nx-proxy-create.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>To expose this new Proxy repository in a Repository Group, create
      a new Nexus Repository group or select an existing group by clicking on
      Repositories in the left-hand Nexus menu. Click on a repository group
      and then select the Configuration tab to display the form shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-archiva-proxy-to-group" />. In the Configuration tab you
      will see a list of Order Group Repositories and Available Repositories.
      Click and drag your new Nexus Proxy repository to the list of Ordered
      Group Repositories, and click Save.</para>

      <figure id="fig-archiva-proxy-to-group">
        <title>Adding a Proxy Repository to a Repository Group</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/archiva-nx-repo-group-proxy.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/archiva-nx-repo-group-proxy.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Next, you will need to define repository groups that will tell
      Nexus to only locate certain artifacts in the newly created proxy
      repository. In , Archiva defined three patterns that were used to filter
      artifacts available from the proxy connector. These three patterns were
      "javax/**", "com/sun/**", and "org/jvnet/**". To recreate this behavior
      in Nexus, define three Routes which will be applied to the group you
      configured in <xref linkend="fig-archiva-proxy-to-group" />. To create a
      route, log in as an administrative user, and click on Routes under the
      Administration menu in the left-hand Nexus menu. Click on Add.. and add
      three inclusive routes that will apply to the repository group you
      configured in <xref linkend="fig-archiva-proxy-to-group" />.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Defining Nexus Repository Groups</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/archiva-nx-repo-routes.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/archiva-nx-repo-routes.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>
</appendix>
