<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.discursive.com/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<appendix id="artifactory">
  <title>Migrating to Nexus from Artifactory</title>

  <section id="artifactory-sect-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Artifactory, migrating from</primary>
      </indexterm>This appendix walks you through the process of using the
    <indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus plugin</primary>

        <secondary>Nexus Migration plugin</secondary>
      </indexterm>Nexus Migration Plugin to migrate an existing Artifactory
    installation to a new Nexus installation. The Nexus Migration Plugin can
    read an Artifactory System Export archive and recreate groups and
    repositories based on your existing Artifactory installation. Once the
    migration is completed, the Nexus Artifactory Bridge will then serve
    repository artifacts to clients using a web application, exposing the same
    artifacts to clients using the same URLs and repository identifier that
    they referenced in your legacy Artifactory installation. This Nexus
    Migration plugin offers an easy, drop-in replacement for
    Artifactory.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="artifactory-sect-create-backup">
    <title>Creating an Artifactory Backup</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Artifactory, migrating from</primary>

        <secondary>system export</secondary>
      </indexterm>The Nexus Migration Plugin relies on the Artifactory System
    Export which is an ZIP archive containing all of the configuration and
    data for an Artifactory installation. To generate this export, log in as
    an administrative user in Artifactory, and click on the
    <guibutton>System</guibutton> link under <guilabel>Import &amp;
    Export</guilabel> in the left navigation menu. Clicking on this link will
    show the <guilabel>Entire System Export &amp; Import</guilabel> screen as
    shown in <xref linkend="fig-creating-artifactory-backup" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-creating-artifactory-backup">
      <title>Creating an Artifactory System Export</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/artifactory_creating-backup.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/artifactory_creating-backup.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This appendix assumes that Artifactory has been installed in the
    directory
    <filename>/usr/local/artifactory-${artifactory.version}</filename>. To
    create a backup ZIP archive in that same directory:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enter
        <filename>/usr/local/artifactory-${artifactory.version}</filename>
        into the <guilabel>Target export dir</guilabel> field. If you are on a
        Windows platform, or if you have installed Artifactory in a different
        path, enter the path at which Artifactory is installed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Check the <guilabel>Create a zip archive (slow!)</guilabel>
        checkbox as shown in <xref
        linkend="fig-creating-artifactory-backup" />.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click the <guibutton>Export</guibutton> button.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>When you click the <guibutton>Export</guibutton> button, Artifactory
    is going to create a timestamped ZIP archive in the specified directory.
    In this example, Artifactory creates a file named
    <filename>/usr/local/artifactory-${artifactory.version}/20100222.154349.zip</filename>.
    Once this step is completed, you will no longer need to run Artifactory,
    and you can safely shut it down. In the next section you will learn how to
    install the Nexus Migration Plugin.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="artifactory-sect-installation">
    <title>Installation of the Migration Plugin and Artifactory Bridge</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

        <secondary>installation of</secondary>
      </indexterm>The migration plugin is a free, open-source plugin that can
    be downloaded by visiting <ulink
    url="http://nexus.sonatype.org/downloads/">http://nexus.sonatype.org/downloads/</ulink>
    and downloading ${nexus.migration.package}.</para>

    <note>
      <para>This section assumes that you have just downloaded and installed
      Nexus Open Source or Nexus Professional. If you haven't installed Nexus,
      you should make a bookmark for this section and jump to <xref
      linkend="install" />. Once you have installed Nexus, return to this
      section and install the Nexus Migration Plugin.</para>
    </note>

    <para>The following screen listing shows a series of commands which can be
    used to install the Nexus Migration plugin into an existing Nexus
    installation. This listing assumes that the environment variable
    <varname>\${NEXUS_HOME}</varname> points to an existing Nexus
    installation. Download the Nexus Migration plugin, copy the distribution
    archive to the Nexus installation folder, and unpack it. This archive will
    install the necessary applications and plugins to enable a smooth
    migration from Artifactory to Nexus.</para>

    <screen>$<command> wget http://nexus.sonatype.org/downloads/\ 
   ${nexus.migration.package}
</command>
...
Resolving repository.sonatype.org... 63.246.20.88
Connecting to repository.sonatype.org|63.246.20.88|:80... connected.
HTTP request sent, awaiting response... 200 OK
Length: 280179 (274K)
Saving to: '${nexus.migration.package}'

100%[======================================&gt;] 280,179      406K/s   in 0.7s    

2009-03-14 15:03:52 (406 KB/s) - \
    `${nexus.migration.package}' saved [280179/280179]
$ <command>cp ${nexus.migration.package} \${NEXUS_HOME}</command>
$ <command>cd \${NEXUS_HOME}</command>
$ <command>unzip ${nexus.migration.package}</command>
Archive:  ${nexus.migration.package}
   creating: runtime/
   creating: runtime/apps/
   creating: runtime/apps/artifactory-bridge/
   creating: runtime/apps/artifactory-bridge/webapp/
   creating: runtime/apps/artifactory-bridge/webapp/WEB-INF/
  inflating: runtime/apps/artifactory-bridge/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml
   creating: conf/
  inflating: conf/jetty.xml
   creating: runtime/apps/nexus/
   creating: runtime/apps/nexus/plugin-repository/
   creating: .../nexus-migration-plugin-artifactory-1.2/
...
   creating: runtime/apps/nexus/lib/
  inflating: .../nexus-migration-plugin-configuration-1.2.jar
  inflating: .../nexus-migration-plugin-artifactory-bridge-1.2.jar
</screen>

    <warning>
      <para>The Nexus Migration plugin archive contains a copy of
      <filename>conf/jetty.xml</filename>. If you have customized jetty.xml
      you will want to make a backup of your customized
      <filename>jetty.xml</filename> before you install this Migration plugin.
      Most people using the Nexus Migration plugin are going to be setting up
      a new instance of Nexus so this shouldn't be an issue.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>Once the Nexus Migration plugin has been installed, start up Nexus
    and go to the Nexus URL. If you are just setting up Nexus, and you've
    skipped the installation chapter, the default Nexus URL is <ulink
    url="http://localhost:8081/nexus">http://localhost:8081/nexus</ulink> and
    the default administrative username/password combination is "admin" and
    "admin123". If the Nexus Migration Plugin is installed properly, you
    should see the <guilabel>Artifactory Import</guilabel> link under
    <guilabel>Administration</guilabel> in the Nexus application menu as shown
    in <xref linkend="fig-artifactory-import-panel" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-artifactory-import-panel">
      <title>Artifactory Import Panel from the Nexus Migration Plugin</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/artifactory_after-installation.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/artifactory_after-installation.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="artifactory-sect-importing">
    <title>Importing an Artifactory System Backup</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

        <secondary>importing Artifactory backup</secondary>
      </indexterm>To import the backup created in <xref
    linkend="artifactory-sect-create-backup" />, enter the path to the
    Artifactory system backup archive in the <guilabel>Artifactory
    Import</guilabel> panel as shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-artifactory-import-backup" />. This path references a
    filesystem path on the same server that is running Nexus.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Please note that the filesystem path in Step 1 of the Artifactory
      Import process references a path on the same server that is running
      Nexus. This field is not a file upload field, and you are not uploading
      the Artifactory System Backup archive from your local machine to the
      server. The Artifactory system export archive can be rather large, and
      the assumption of the Nexus Migration plugin is that you are installing
      Nexus on the same server that had previously run Artifactory. If you are
      not installing Nexus on the same server, you must upload the Artifactory
      System Backup ZIP file to the Nexus server prior to typing in the
      filesystem path shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-artifactory-import-backup" />.</para>
    </note>

    <figure id="fig-artifactory-import-backup">
      <title>Specifying the Artifactory System Backup Path</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/artifactory_import-artifactory-backup.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/artifactory_import-artifactory-backup.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Click the <guibutton>Import</guibutton> button, and Nexus will then
    examine the Artifactory System Backup archive and populate fields in Step
    2 of the Artifactory Import panel.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="artifactory-sect-configuring">
    <title>Configuring the Artifactory Import</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

        <secondary>configuring Artifactory backup</secondary>
      </indexterm>Once the System Backup has been imported, the Nexus
    Migration plugin will populate the Groups, Repositories, and Users tables
    in Step 2 of the Artifactory Import panel as shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-artifactory-configuring-import" />. These tables and form
    elements allow you to customize which repositories and groups are going to
    be imported into Nexus and how Nexus will configure corresponding
    repositories. The following sections describe each of these configuration
    tables in detail.</para>

    <figure id="fig-artifactory-configuring-import">
      <title>Configuring the Artifactory Import</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/artifactory_customer-import-step2.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/artifactory_customer-import-step2.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <section id="artifactory-sect-configuring-groups">
      <title>Configuring Artifactory Group Imports</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

          <secondary>configuring group imports</secondary>
        </indexterm>The groups table displays all of the groups contained in
      the Artifactory system backup. By default, all groups are selected. If
      you wish to omit an Artifactory group from the import process, deselect
      the checkbox for that group in the Import column. Each group's content
      type resolution is shown in the Content Type Resolution column. Changing
      the content type resolution will control how Nexus configures the Nexus
      Group that corresponds to each Artifactory Group.</para>

      <figure id="fig-artifactory-configuring-groups">
        <title>Configuring Artifactory Group Imports</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/artifactory_groups-content-type.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/artifactory_groups-content-type.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="fig-artifactory-config-repository-imports">
      <title>Configuring Artifactory Repository Imports</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

          <secondary>configuring repository imports</secondary>
        </indexterm>The second table in Step 2 of the Artifactory Import panel
      is the Repositories panel. In this panel you can select repositories to
      import and also configure how Artifactory proxy repositories would be
      mapped to Nexus proxy repository with matching canonical URLs. Each row
      in the Repositories table contains the following columns:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Import</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This column contains a simple checkbox. If the checkbox is
            checked, the repository will be imported into Nexus. If the
            checkbox is not check, the Nexus Migration plugin will omit the
            repository from the import process.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Repository ID</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This is the repository identifier from Artifactory. This
            column cannot be edited.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Type</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This is the type of the repository being imported. Hosted
            repositories in Artifactory will be imported as hosted
            repositories in Nexus. Proxy repositories in Artifactory will be
            imported as proxy repositories in Nexus unless they are merged
            with an existing proxy repository.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Map URLs</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Since Nexus is a drop-in replacement for Artifactory, the
            Nexus Migration Plugin gives you the option to Map the legacy
            Artifactory URLs to the newer Nexus URLs. Checking this box will
            tell the Nexus Migration plugin to create the appropriate URL
            mappings to allow clients to interact with the newly created Nexus
            repositories via the legacy Artifactory URLs.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Copy Cached Artifacts</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Checking this box will tell the Nexus Migration plugin to
            copy the cache contents of a proxy repository to the newly created
            Nexus repository. Leaving this box unchecked will tell the Nexus
            Migration plugin to only copy the configuration for a proxy
            repository.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Releases/Snapshots</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This allows you to customize the Repository Policy in a
            newly created Nexus repository. If you want a hosted or proxy
            repository to serve only release or snapshot versions, select the
            corresponding value in the dropdown. If you want a host or proxy
            repository to serve both release and snapshot versions, select
            both in this dropdown list. If you want Nexus to use the type
            implied by the Artifactory repository, don't select a value in
            this dropdown.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <figure id="fig-artifactory-configuring-repo">
        <title>Configuring Repositories for Artifactory Import</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/artifactory_repository-releases-snapshots.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/artifactory_repository-releases-snapshots.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Merge With</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If an Artifactory proxy repository has a canonical URL which
            matches the canonical URL of an existing Nexus repository, you can
            merge this proxy repository into the existing Nexus proxy
            repository. Most people running the Artifactory Import process
            will likely have a <varname>repo1</varname> proxy repository in
            Artifactory for the Maven Central Repository and a
            <varname>central</varname> proxy repository in Nexus for the Maven
            Central Repository. As both of these repositories have the same
            URL, the Nexus Migration plugin will show a checkbox in the
            <guilabel>Merge With</guilabel> column as shown in <xref
            linkend="fig-artifactory-merge-with" />. Checking this box will
            instruct the Nexus Migration plugin to merge the contents and
            configuration of the <varname>repo1</varname> repository with the
            existing <varname>central</varname> repository. In other words, if
            this box is checked, the Nexus Migration plugin will not create a
            new proxy repository for <varname>repo1</varname>, and if the box
            isn't checked, the Nexus Migration plugin will create new proxy
            repository for <varname>repo1</varname>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <figure id="fig-artifactory-merge-with">
        <title>Merging a Proxy Repository During Artifactory Import</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/artifactory_merging-proxy-repos.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/artifactory_merging-proxy-repos.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring Users and Privileges in the Artifactory
      Import</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

          <secondary>configuring users and privileges</secondary>
        </indexterm>The Users table shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-artifactory-configuring-users" /> allows you to select
      which users are imported into Nexus from the Artifactory system backup
      archive. The columns in the User table are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Import</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If the checkbox in this column is selected, the Artifactory
            user will be imported into Nexus, if the box is not selected this
            user will not be imported into Nexus.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>User ID</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This is the User identifier from Artifactory, this field
            cannot be edited.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Email</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This is the email of a User, this field cannot be
            edited.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Admin</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If this checkbox is selected, Nexus will associate the newly
            imported user with the Nexus Administrator role.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <figure id="fig-artifactory-configuring-users">
        <title>Configuring Users During Artifactory Import</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/artifactory_user-import.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/artifactory_user-import.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Just below the Users table is the <guilabel>Import
      Permissions</guilabel> checkbox. If this checkbox is selected, Nexus
      will attempt to import Artifactory privileges into Nexus and map the
      corresponding roles and privileges to the imported users.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="artifactory-sect-perform-import">
    <title>Performing the Artifactory Import</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

        <secondary>performing import</secondary>
      </indexterm>Once the Artifactory import has been configured, click on
    the <guibutton>Start Import</guibutton> button at the bottom of the
    <guilabel>Artifactory Import</guilabel> panel. Clicking on the
    <guibutton>Start Import</guibutton> button will show you the warning
    dialog shown in <xref linkend="fig-artifactory-loading-warning" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-artifactory-loading-warning">
      <title>Loading Artifactory Configuration Warning</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/artifactory_warning-long-time.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/artifactory_warning-long-time.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If you are migrating a large Artifactory installation, the loading
    process could take a significant amount of time. If you are comfortable
    with your import configuration, click on the <guibutton>Yes</guibutton>
    button. Clicking on the <guibutton>Yes</guibutton> button will then cause
    Nexus to display the dialog shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-artifactory-import-scheduled" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-artifactory-import-scheduled">
      <title>Artifactory Import Scheduled Dialog</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/artifactory_import-scheduled.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/artifactory_import-scheduled.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This dialog informs you that the import is scheduled to start as
    soon as possible using the Nexus scheduled Job execution infrastructure.
    You can check on the progress of the import process by clicking on the
    <guibutton>Show Log</guibutton> button at the bottom of the
    <guilabel>Artifactory Import</guilabel> panel or by clicking on
    <guilabel>Logs and Config Files</guilabel> under the
    <guimenu>Views/Repositories</guimenu> menu and selecting the
    <filename>migration.log</filename> file from the "Select a document..."
    dropdown. The migration log is shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-artifactory-migration-log" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-artifactory-migration-log">
      <title>Viewing the Migration Logs</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/artifactory_migration-log.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/artifactory_migration-log.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="artifactory-sect-bridge">
    <title>Configuring Artifactory Clients to Use Nexus</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Migration plugin</primary>

        <secondary>configuring Artifactory clients</secondary>
      </indexterm>Nexus is a drop-in replacement for Artifactory, this means
    that you don't need to reconfigure your project's
    <filename>settings.xml</filename> and repository elements throughout your
    POMs to start using Nexus. When you installed the Nexus Migration plugin,
    you also installed a web application called the Artifactory Bridge which
    should be running under the context path <filename>/artifactory</filename>
    next to the <filename>/nexus</filename> application. If you run Nexus at
    the default <ulink
    url="http://localhost:8081/nexus/">http://localhost:8081/nexus/</ulink>
    URL, the artifactory bridge will be running at <ulink
    url="http://localhost:8081/artifactory/">http://localhost:8081/artifactory/</ulink>.</para>

    <para>This Artifactory Bridge will serve repository metadata and artifacts
    from Nexus under the same URLs that your existing Artifactory clients
    expect. When you were configuring your repositories during the Artifactory
    Import in <xref linkend="fig-artifactory-config-repository-imports" />,
    you'll remember that there was a column named <guilabel>Map
    URL</guilabel>. Clicking on this <guilabel>Map URL</guilabel> check box
    for a repository instructed the Nexus Migration plugin to configure a
    mapping between the old Artifactory URL and repository identifier and the
    new Nexus URL and repository identifier.</para>

    <para>To see this mapping in action, take a look at the Central repository
    through three different URLs. This example assumes that you mapped your
    old <varname>repo1</varname> Artifactory proxy repository to the Nexus
    <varname>central</varname> proxy repository. Let's take a quick look at
    the URL for <filename>metadata.xml</filename> for the
    <varname>nexus-index</varname> artifact which is under the group
    identifier <varname>org.sonatype.nexus</varname>. To retrieve this
    directly from the Maven Central repository, you would use the following
    URL:</para>

    <screen>http://repo1.maven.org/maven2/\
org/sonatype/nexus/nexus-indexer/maven-metadata.xml</screen>

    <para>To reterieve the same file from the Nexus <varname>central</varname>
    proxy of the Maven Central repository, you would use the following URL
    which contains the new Nexus repository identifier "central":</para>

    <screen>http://localhost:8081/nexus/content/repositories/central/\
org/sonatype/nexus/nexus-indexer/maven-metadata.xml</screen>

    <para>To retrieve the same file from the Artifactory Bridge, you would use
    the following URL which contains the old Artifactory repository identifier
    "repo1":</para>

    <screen>http://localhost:8081/artifactory/repo1/\
org/sonatype/nexus/nexus-indexer/maven-metadata.xml</screen>

    <para>The configuration for these mappings is stored in
    <filename>sonatype-work/nexus/conf/mapping.xml</filename>. This is an XML
    file which was configured during the import that maps the old Artifactory
    repository identifiers to the new Nexus repository identifiers. The
    Artifactory Bridge web application is configured in
    <filename>\${NEXUS_HOME}/conf/plexus.xml</filename> contains a reference
    to the web application and also configures the context-path
    <filename>/artifactory</filename>.</para>
  </section>
</appendix>
