<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.discursive.com/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="security">
  <title>Managing Maven Settings</title>

  <section id="settings-sect-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Maven settings</primary>

        <secondary>management of</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus plugin</primary>

        <secondary>Maven Settings plugin</secondary>
      </indexterm>Nexus Professional allows you to define templates for Maven
    Settings and use Nexus as a way to distribute updates to a global Maven
    Settings template. When you move an organization to a repository manager
    such as Nexus, one of the constant challenges is keeping everyone's Maven
    Settings synchronized. If a Nexus administrator makes a change which
    requires every developer to modify his or her ~/.m2/settings.xml file,
    this feature can be used to manage the distribution of Maven Settings
    changes to the entire organization. Once you have defined a Maven Settings
    template in Nexus Professional, developers can then use the Nexus Maven
    plugin to retrieve the new Maven Settings file directly from Nexus
    Professional.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="settings-sect-install">
    <title>Manage Maven Settings Templates</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Maven settings</primary>

        <secondary>templates</secondary>
      </indexterm>To manage Maven Settings templates, click on Maven Settings
    in the Enterprise section of the Nexus menu on the left side of the Nexus
    UI. Clicking on Maven Settings will load the panel shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-settings-maven-settings" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-settings-maven-settings">
      <title>The Maven Settings Panel</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/settings_managing-templates.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/settings_managing-templates.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The Maven Settings panel allows you to add, delete, and edit a Maven
    Settings template. The default template has an id of "default" and is
    read-only, it contains the recommended settings for a standard Nexus
    installation. To create a new Maven Settings template, click on the Add...
    button and select "Settings Template". Once the new template is created,
    assign a name to the template and click the Save button.</para>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Maven settings</primary>

        <secondary>template variables</secondary>
      </indexterm>To edit a template, click on a template that is not read
    only, and edit the template in the Maven Settings panel. Once you are
    finished editing the template, click Save to save the template. When
    editing the template, the following variables are available:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>\${baseurl}</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This variable will be replaced with the base URL of the Nexus
          installation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>\${userId}</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This variable will be replaced with the user id of the user
          that is generating a Maven Settings file from this template.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>To preview a Maven Settings template, click on the Template URL in
    the table of Maven Settings templates. Clicking on this URL will load a
    dialog window which contains the Maven Settings file generated from this
    template. This rendered view of the Maven Settings template will have all
    variable references replaced using the current context of the user:
    \${baseurl} will be replaced with the Base URL of the current Nexus
    installation, and \${userId} will be replaced with the user id of the
    current user.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Downloading Maven Settings with the Nexus Maven Plugin</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Maven plugin</primary>

        <secondary>downloading Maven settings</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Maven settings</primary>

        <secondary>Nexus Maven plugin</secondary>
      </indexterm>Once you have defined a set of Maven templates, you can use
    the Nexus Maven plugin to distribute changes to the Maven Settings file to
    the entire organization.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Running the Nexus Maven Plugin</title>

      <para>To invoke goals in the Nexus Maven plugin, you will want to add
      the appropriate plugin group to your Maven settings file. Add the
      org.sonatype.plugins groupId to ~/.m2/settings.xml as shown in <xref
      linkend="ex-settings-nexus-plugin-group" />.</para>

      <example id="ex-settings-nexus-plugin-group">
        <title>Adding org.sonatype.plugins to pluginGroups in Maven
        Settings</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;settings&gt;
  ...
  &lt;pluginGroups&gt;
    &lt;pluginGroup&gt;org.sonatype.plugins&lt;/pluginGroup&gt;
  &lt;/pluginGroups&gt;
  ...
&lt;/settings&gt;</programlisting>
      </example>

      <note>
        <para>It might seem ironic that you need to update your Maven Settings
        to take advantage of a plugin which will be used to manage your Maven
        Settings file. Adding this plugin definition is a task that only needs
        to be completed once to add the appropriate plugin group for the Nexus
        Maven plugin. Once you have successfully configured your Maven
        Settings, you will be replacing your Maven Settings with templates
        from Nexus Professional. Every default template in Nexus Professional
        adds the org.sonatype.plugins group to the pluginGroups, and it is
        essential that you make sure that any new, custom templates also
        include this plugin group definition. Otherwise, there is a chance
        that a developer could update his or her Maven Settings and lose the
        ability to use the Nexus Maven plugin.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Adding the org.sonatype.plugins group to your Maven Settings will
      allow you to run the following goals from the Nexus Maven Plugin:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>nexus:settings-download</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This goal downloads a Maven Settings template from Nexus
            Professional and stores it on a local machine. This goal can be
            configured to update a user's ~/.m2/settings.xml file or the
            global configuration file which is stored the Maven installation
            directory. If you are replacing a Maven Settings file, this goal
            can also be configured to make a backup of an existing Maven
            Settings file.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Once you have configured the pluginGroup in your Maven Settings
      file, you can run the Nexus Maven plugin from the command line.</para>

      <screen>$ mvn nexus:settings-download
</screen>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring Nexus Maven Plugin for Settings Management</title>

      <para>The Settings Management goal in the Nexus Maven plugin requires
      security credentials and a base URL for the Nexus server you are
      interacting with. You can specify security credentials by supplying a
      username and password or by supplying a server id that corresponds to a
      server in your Maven Settings (~/.m2/settings.xml). The common
      configuration parameters and security configuration properties
      are:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>nexusURL</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Points to the Nexus server installation's base URL. If you
            have installed Nexus on your local machine, this would be
            http://localhost:8081/nexus/</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>username</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Username to use for authenticating to Nexus. Default value
            is \${user.name}.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>password</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Password to use for authenticating to Nexus</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>serverAuthId</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>You should specify either username and password or the
            serverAuthId. If you specify a value for serverAuthId, the Nexus
            Maven plugin is going to look at the contents of your
            <filename>~/.m2/settings.xml</filename> file and use the username
            and password from a server definition.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>In most cases a valid user login will be required to access your
      settings templates. By default, if you don't specify the nexusURL and
      password parameters, the plugin will prompt you for them. If you don't
      specify the username parameter, the Java System property
      <varname>\${user.name}</varname> will be used.</para>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus Maven plugin</primary>

          <secondary>settings configuration</secondary>
        </indexterm>In addition to these security options, all of the Maven
      Settings management goal has the following configuration
      parameters:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>verboseDebug</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If verboseDebug is set to true Maven will print out debug
            messages that detail the plugin's interaction with Nexus.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>backupFormat</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When backing up an existing settings.xml file, use this date
            format in conjunction with SimpleDateFormat to construct a new
            filename of the form: settings.xml.$(format). Datestamps are used
            for backup copies of the settings.xml to avoid overwriting
            previously backed up settings files. This protects against the
            case where the download mojo is used multiple times with incorrect
            settings, where using a single static backup-file name would
            destroy the original, pre-existing settings. Default value is:
            yyyyMMdd_HHmmss.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>destination</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The standard destination where the downloaded settings.xml
            template should be saved. If the destination is "global", the
            Nexus Maven plugin will save the Maven Settings file to
            \${M2_HOME}/conf. Is the destination is "user", the Nexus Maven
            plugin will save the Maven Settings file to ~/.m2/settings.xml. If
            the target parameter is set, it will override this value. Default
            value is: user.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>doBackup</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If true and there is a pre-existing settings.xml file in the
            way of this download, backup the file to a datestamped filename,
            where the specific format of the datestamp is given by the
            backupFormat parameter. Default value is: true.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>encoding</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Use this parameter to define a non-default encoding for the
            settings file.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>target</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If set, ignore the standard location given by the
            destination parameter, and use this file location to save the
            settings template instead. If this file exists, it will be backed
            up using the same logic as the standard locations (using the
            doBackup and backupFormat parameters).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>url</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The full URL of a settings template available from a
            particular Nexus Professional instance. If missing, the mojo will
            prompt for this value.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Downloading Maven Settings</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Maven settings</primary>

          <secondary>downloading from Nexus</secondary>
        </indexterm>To download Maven Settings from Nexus Profession, you will
      need to know the URL of the Maven Settings template. If you omit this
      URL on the command-line, the Nexus Maven plugin will prompt you for a
      URL when it is executed:</para>

      <screen>$ <command>mvn nexus:settings-download</command>
[INFO] [nexus:settings-download]
Settings Template URL: <command>\
.../nexus/service/local/templates/settings/default/content</command>
[INFO] Existing settings backed up to: \
   /Users/tobrien/.m2/settings.xml.20090408_204422
[INFO] Settings saved to: /Users/tobrien/.m2/settings.xml</screen>

      <para>Alternatively, you can specify the username, password, and URL on
      the command line.</para>

      <screen>$ <command>export NX_URL="http://localhost:8080/nexus/"</command>
$ <command>mvn nexus:settings-download \
      -Durl=\${NX_URL}/service/local/templates/settings/default/content \
      -Dusername=admin \
      -Dpassword=admin123</command></screen>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
