<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.discursive.com/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="using">
  <title>Using Nexus</title>

  <section id="using-sect-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Nexus provides for <indexterm>
        <primary>anonymous access</primary>
      </indexterm>anonymous access for users who only need to search
    repositories, browse repositories, and peruse the system feeds. This
    anonymous access level changes the navigation menu and some of the options
    available when you right-click on a repository. This read-only access
    displays a user interface shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-repoman-anonymous-interface" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-repoman-anonymous-interface">
      <title>Nexus Interface for Anonymous Users</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/repository-manager_public-interface.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/repository-manager_public-interface.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="using-sect-browsing">
    <title>Browsing Repositories</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>browsing repositories</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus repository</primary>

        <secondary>browsing storage</secondary>
      </indexterm>One of the most straightforward uses of the Nexus is to
    browse the structure of a Maven repository. If you click on the Browse
    Repositories menu item in the Views menu, you should see the following
    display. The top-half of <xref linkend="fig-nexus-browse-repo" /> shows
    you a list of groups and repositories along with the type of the
    repository and the repository status. To browse the artifacts that are
    stored in a local Nexus instance, click on the Browse Storage tab for a
    repository as shown in <xref linkend="fig-nexus-browse-repo" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-nexus-browse-repo">
      <title>Browsing a Nexus Repository</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/repository-manager_browse-repositories.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/repository-manager_browse-repositories.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>When you are browsing a repository, you can right click on any file
    and download it directly to your browser. This allows you to retrieve
    specific artifacts manually, or examine a <acronym>POM</acronym> file in
    the browser.</para>

    <note>
      <para>When browsing a remote repository you might notice that the tree
      doesn't contain all of the artifacts in a repository. When you browse a
      proxy repository, Nexus is displaying the artifacts which have been
      cached locally from the remote repository. If you don't see an artifact
      you expected to see through Nexus, it only means that Nexus has yet to
      cache the artifact locally. If you have enabled remote repository index
      downloads, Nexus will return search results that may include artifacts
      not yet downloaded from the remote repository. <xref
      linkend="fig-nexus-browse-repo" />, is just an example, and you may or
      may not have the <varname>doxia-core </varname> artifact available in
      your installation of Nexus.</para>
    </note>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus repository</primary>

        <secondary>browsing index</secondary>
      </indexterm>A Nexus proxy repository acts as a local cache for a remote
    repository, in addition to downloading and caching artifacts locally,
    Nexus will also download an index of all the artifacts stored in a
    particular repository. When searching or browsing for artifacts, it is
    often more useful to search and browse the repository index. To view the
    repository index, click on the Browse Index tab for a particular
    repository to load the interface shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-nexus-browse-repo-index" />.</para>

    <figure floatstyle="" id="fig-nexus-browse-repo-index">
      <title>Browsing a Nexus Repository Index</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/repository-manager_browse-repository-index.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/repository-manager_browse-repository-index.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>As shown in <xref linkend="fig-nexus-browse-repo-index" />, if an
    artifact has been downloaded from a remote repository and cached in Nexus,
    the artifact or folder will display a small Nexus logo.</para>

    <section id="using-dependencies">
      <title>View Artifact Dependencies</title>

      <para>Nexus Professional provides you with the ability to browse an
      artifact's dependencies. Using the artifact metadata found in an
      artifact's POM, Nexus will scan a repository or a repository group and
      attempt to resolve and display an artifact's dependencies. To view an
      artifact's dependencies, browse the repository storage or the repository
      index, select an artifact (or an artifact's POM), and then click on the
      Maven Dependency tab.</para>

      <para>On the Maven Dependency tab, you will see the following form
      elements:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Repository</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When resolving an artifact's dependencies, Nexus will query
            an existing repository or repository group. In many cases it will
            make sense to select the same repository group you are referencing
            in your Maven Settings. If you encounter any problems during the
            dependency resolution, you need to make sure that you are
            referencing a repository or a group which contains these
            dependencies.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Mode</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An artifact's dependencies can be list as either a tree or a
            list. When dependencies are displayed in a tree, you can inspect
            direct dependencies and transitive dependencies. This can come in
            handy if you are assessing an artifact based on the dependencies
            it is going to pull into your project's build. When you list
            dependencies as a list, Nexus is going to perform the same process
            used by Maven to collapse a tree of dependencies into a list of
            dependencies using rules to merge and override dependency versions
            if there are any overlaps or conflicts.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Once you have selected a repository to resolve against and a mode
      to display an artifact's dependencies, click on the Resolve button as
      shown in <xref linkend="fig-using-dependencies" />. Clicking on this
      button will start the process of resolving dependencies, depending on
      the number of artifacts already cached by Nexus, this process can take
      anywhere from a few seconds to minute. Once the resolution process is
      finished, you should see the artifact's dependencies as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-using-dependencies" />.</para>

      <figure floatstyle="" id="fig-using-dependencies">
        <title>View an Artifact's Dependencies</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/using_dependencies.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/using_dependencies.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Once you have resolved an artifact's dependencies, you can double
      click on a row in the tree or list of dependencies to navigate to other
      artifacts within the Nexus interface.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="using-sect-viewing-metadata">
      <title>Viewing Artifact Metadata</title>

      <para>Nexus Professional gives you the ability to view artifact
      metadata. When browsing repository storage or a repository index,
      clicking on an artifact will load the Artifact Information panel.
      Selecting the Artifact Metadata tab will display the interface shown in
      <xref linkend="fig-using-viewing-metadata" />.</para>

      <figure floatstyle="" id="fig-using-viewing-metadata">
        <title>Viewing Artifact Metadata</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/meta_existing-meta-value.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/meta_existing-meta-value.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Artifact metadata consists of a key, a value, and a namespace.
      Existing metadata from an artifact's POM is given a urn:maven namespace,
      and custom attributes are stored under the urn:nexus/user
      namespace.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="using-sect-editing-metadata">
      <title>Editing Artifact Metadata</title>

      <para>Nexus Professional gives you the ability to add custom attributes
      to artifact metadata. To add a custom attribute, click on an artifact in
      Nexus, and select the Artifact Metadata tab. On the Artifact Metadata
      tab, click on the Add... button and a new row will be inserted into the
      list of attributes. Supply a key and value and click the Save button to
      update an artifact's metadata. <xref
      linkend="fig-using-editing-metadata" /> shows the Artifact Metadata
      panel with two custom attributes: "approvedBy" and "approved".</para>

      <figure floatstyle="" id="fig-using-editing-metadata">
        <title>Editing Artifact Metadata</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/meta_setting-meta-value.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/meta_setting-meta-value.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="using-sect-browsing-groups">
    <title>Browsing Groups</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>browsing groups</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Repository Groups</primary>

        <secondary>browsing storage</secondary>
      </indexterm>Nexus contains ordered groups of repositories which allow
    you to expose a series of repositories through a single
    <acronym>URL</acronym>. More often than not, an organization is going to
    point Maven at the two default Nexus groups: Public Repositories and
    Public Snapshot Repositories. Most end-users of Nexus are not going to
    know what artifacts are being served from what specific repository, and
    they are going to want to be able to browse the Public Repository. To
    support this use case, Maven allows you to browse the contents of a Nexus
    Group as if it were a single merged repository with a tree structure.
    <xref linkend="fig-nexus-browse-group" />, shows the browsing storage
    interface for a Nexus Group. There is no difference to the user experience
    of browsing a Nexus Group vs. browsing a Nexus Repository.</para>

    <figure id="fig-nexus-browse-group">
      <title>Browsing a Nexus Group</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/repository-manager_browse-group.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/repository-manager_browse-group.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>When browsing a Nexus group's storage, you are browsing the
    underlying storage for all of the repositories which are contained in a
    group. If a Nexus group contains proxy repositories, the Browse Storage
    tab will show all of the artifacts in the Nexus group that have been
    download from the remote repositories. <indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Repository Groups</primary>

        <secondary>browsing index</secondary>
      </indexterm>To browse and search all artifacts available in a Nexus
    group, click on the Browse Index tab to load the interface shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-nexus-browse-group-index" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-nexus-browse-group-index">
      <title>Browsing a Nexus Group Index</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/repository-manager_browse-group-index.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/repository-manager_browse-group-index.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="using-sect-searching">
    <title>Searching for Artifacts</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>artifact search</primary>
      </indexterm>In the left-hand navigation area, there is an Artifact
    Search text field next to a magnifying glass. To search for an artifact by
    groupId or artifactId, type in some text and click the magnifying glass.
    Typing in the search term "guice" and clicking the magnifying glass should
    yield a search result similar to <xref
    linkend="fig-nexus-search" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-nexus-search">
      <title>Results of an Artifact Search for "guice"</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/search-results.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="figs/print/search-initial.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Once you've located the artifact you were looking for you can click
    on the pom link to download the POM or the artifact link to download the
    artifact.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Look at the Version column in the search results. In this
        version of the search interface, we decided to list the most recent
        version. If you need to view a different version, click on "Show All
        Versions". Clicking on "Show All Versions" will drill down into the
        list of available versions.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Look at the Download column in the search results. This Download
        column contains direct download links for the most recent version of
        the artifact. To download a matching artifact, just click on a link in
        this column.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Select a search result, and you will see the artifact in the
        Repository Tree in the lower left-hand quadrant of this interface.
        This is helpful to give you context for an artifact. An artifact could
        be present in more than one repository. If this is the case, click on
        the value next to "Viewing Repository" to switch between multiple
        matching repositories.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In the lower right-hand quadrant of the interface, you will see
        a number of tabs which show information about the selected search
        result:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Maven Information: This contains basic identifiers and a
            snippet of XML you can use to add this artifact as a project
            dependency.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Archive Browser (Nexus Professional): This gives you a way
            to explore the contents of an archive in the repository. You can
            view the files and folders contained in a matching search
            result.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Artifact Information: This tab contains timestampes, file
            size, checksum values, and a list of repositories containing a
            given artifact.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Artifact Metadata (Nexus Professional): This tab shows all
            of the built-in and custom metadata associated with an
            artifact.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus search</primary>

        <secondary>by groupId</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus search</primary>

        <secondary>by artifactId</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus search</primary>

        <secondary>by class name</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus search</primary>

        <secondary>by checksum</secondary>
      </indexterm>In addition to searching by a groupId or an artifactId,
    Nexus has a feature which allows you to search for an artifact by a
    checksum.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>Let me guess? You installed Nexus, ran to the search box, typed in
      the name of a group or an artifact, pressed search, and saw absolutely
      nothing. No results. Nexus isn't going to retrieve the remote repository
      indexes by default, you need to activate downloading of remote indexes
      for the three proxy repositories that Nexus ships with. Without these
      indexes, Nexus has nothing to search. Find instructions for activating
      index downloads in <xref linkend="config-sect-manage-repo" />.</para>
    </warning>

    <section id="sect-using-opensearch">
      <title>Nexus OpenSearch Integration</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>OpenSearch integration</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus search</primary>

          <secondary>OpenSearch integration</secondary>
        </indexterm>OpenSearch a standard which facilitates searching directly
      from your browser's search box. If you are using Internet Explorer 7+ or
      Firefox 2+ you can add any Nexus instance as an OpenSearch provider.
      Then you can just type in a search term into your browser's search field
      and quickly search for Maven artifacts. To configure OpenSearch, load
      Nexus in a browser and then click on the dropdown next to the search
      tool that is embedded in your browser. <xref
      linkend="fig-using-opensearch-configure" /> shows the Add Nexus option
      that is present in Firefox's OpenSearch provider dropdown.</para>

      <figure id="fig-using-opensearch-configure">
        <title>Configuring Nexus as an OpenSearch Provider</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/using_opensearch-config.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/using_opensearch-config.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Once you have added Nexus to the list of OpenSearch providers,
      click on the dropdown next to the search term and select Nexus
      (localhost) from the list of OpenSearch providers. Type in a groupId,
      artifactId, or portion of a Maven identifier and press enter. Your
      opensearch-friendly web browser will then take you to the search results
      page of Nexus displaying all the artifacts that match your search
      term.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>OpenSearch Search Results in Nexus</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/using_opensearch-search.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/using_opensearch-search.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Once, you have configured your browser to use Nexus as an
      OpenSearch provider, searching for a Maven artifact is as simple as
      typing in a groupId or artifactId, selecting Nexus from the dropdown
      shown in <xref linkend="fig-using-permanent-opensearch-option" />, and
      performing a search.</para>

      <figure id="fig-using-permanent-opensearch-option">
        <title>Nexus Available as an Option in the Firefox OpenSearch Provider
        List</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/using_opensearch-permanent.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/using_opensearch-permanent.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="sect-using-search-metadata">
      <title>Searching Artifact Metadata</title>

      <para>Nexus Professional provides you with the ability to configure
      custom artifact metadata and search for artifacts with specific
      metadata. To search for artifacts using metadata, click on the Advanced
      Search link directly below the search field in the Nexus application
      menu to open the Search panel. Once in the search panel, click on the
      Keyword Search and click on Metadata Search in the search type dropdown
      as shown in <xref linkend="fig-using-search-metadata" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-using-search-metadata">
        <title>Searching Artifact Metadata</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/meta_search-selection.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/meta_search-selection.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Once you select the Metadata Search you will see two search fields
      and an operator dropdown. The two search fields are the key and value of
      the metadata you are searching for. The key corresponds to the key of
      the metadata you are searching for, and the value contains the value or
      value range you are searching for. The operator dropdown can be set to
      Equals, Matches, Bounded, or Not Equal.</para>

      <figure id="fig-using-search-metadata-function">
        <title>Metadata Search Results for Custom Metadata</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/meta_search-function.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/meta_search-function.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>One you locate a matching artfiact in the Metadata Search
      interface, click on the artifact and then select the Artifact Metadata
      to examine an artifacts metadata as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-using-search-metadata-results" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-using-search-metadata-results">
        <title>Metadata Search Results for Custom Metadata</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/meta_search-result.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/meta_search-result.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="using-sect-uploading-artifacts">
    <title>Uploading Artifacts</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus repository</primary>

        <secondary>uploading artifact</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>uploading artifacts</primary>
      </indexterm>When your build makes use of proprietary or custom
    dependencies which are not available from public repositories, you will
    often need to find a way to make them available to developers in a custom
    Maven repository. Nexus ships with a preconfigured 3rd Party repository
    that was designed to hold 3rd Party dependencies which are used in your
    builds. To upload artifacts to a repository, select a hosted repository in
    the Repositories panel and then click on the Artifact Upload tab. Clicking
    on the Artifact Upload tab will display the tab shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-using-artifact-upload" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-using-artifact-upload">
      <title>Artifact Upload Form</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/using_artifact-upload.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/using_artifact-upload.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To upload an artifact, click on Select Artifact(s) for Upload... and
    select one or more artifacts from the filesystem to upload. Once you have
    selected an artifact, you can modify the classifier and the extension
    before clicking on the Add Artifact button. Once you have clicked on the
    Add Artifact button, you can then configure the source of the Group,
    Artifact, Version (GAV) parameters. If the artifact you are uploading is a
    JAR file that was created by Maven it will already have POM information
    embedded in it. If you are uploading a JAR from a vendor you will likely
    need to set the Group Identifier, Artifact Identifier, and Version
    manually. To do this, select GAV Parameters from the GAV Definition
    dropdown at the top of this form. Selecting GAV Parameters will expose a
    set of form fields which will let you set the Group, Artifact, Version,
    and Packaging of the artifacts being uploaded. If you would prefer to set
    the Group, Artifact, and Version from a POM file associated with the
    uploaded artifact, select From POM in the GAV Definition dropdown.
    Selecting From POM in this dropdown will expose a button labeled "Select
    POM to Upload". Once a POM file has been selected for upload, the name of
    the POM file will be displayed in the form field below this button.</para>

    <para>The Artifact Upload panel supports multiple artifacts with the same
    Group, Artifact, and Version identifiers. For example, if you need to
    upload multiple artifacts with different classifiers, you may do so by
    clicking on Select Artifact(s) for Upload and Add Artifact multiple
    times.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="using-sect-browsing-system">
    <title>Browsing System Feeds</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>system feeds</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus administration</primary>

        <secondary>system feeds</secondary>
      </indexterm>Nexus provides feeds that capture system events, you can
    browse these feeds by clicking on System Feeds under the View menu.
    Clicking on System Feeds will show the panel in <xref
    linkend="fig-repoman-system-feeds" />. You can use these simple interface
    to browse the most recent reports of artifact deployments, cached
    artifacts, broken artifacts, and storage changes that have occurred in
    Nexus.</para>

    <figure id="fig-repoman-system-feeds">
      <title>Browsing Nexus System Feeds</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/repository-manager_system-feed.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/repository-manager_system-feed.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" userlevel="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>These feeds can come in handy if you are working at a large
    organization with multiple development teams deploying to the same
    instance of Nexus. If such an arrangement, all developers in an
    organization can subscribe to the <acronym>RSS</acronym> feeds for New
    Deployed Artifacts as a way to ensure that everyone is aware when a new
    release has been pushed to Nexus. Exposing these system events as
    <acronym>RSS</acronym> feeds also opens to the door to other, more
    creative uses of this information, such as connecting Nexus to external
    automated testing systems. To access the <acronym>RSS</acronym> feeds for
    a specific feed, select the feed in the System Feeds view panel and then
    click on the Subscribe button. Nexus will then load the
    <acronym>RSS</acronym> feed in your browse and you can subscribe to the
    feed in your favorite <acronym>RSS</acronym> reader.</para>

    <para>There are six system feeds available in the System Feeds view, and
    each has a <acronym>URL</acronym> which resembles the following
    <acronym>URL</acronym>:</para>

    <screen>http://localhost:8081/nexus/service/local/feeds/recentlyChangedFiles</screen>

    <para>Where <varname>recentChanges</varname> would be replaced with the
    identifier of the feed you were attempting to read. Available system feeds
    include:</para>

    <table>
      <title>Available System Feeds</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colwidth="2.5in" />

        <colspec colwidth="2.5in" />

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Feed Identifier</entry>

            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><varname>authcAuthz</varname></entry>

            <entry>Authentication and Authorization Events</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>brokenArtifacts</varname></entry>

            <entry>Broken Artifacts (Checksum mismatch, missing checksums,
            invalid POMs)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>brokenFiles</varname></entry>

            <entry>Broken Files (Checksum errors.)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>errorWarning</varname></entry>

            <entry>Errors, warnings, and exceptions from Nexus</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>recentlyCachedOrDeployedArtifacts</varname></entry>

            <entry>New artifacts in all repositories (cached or
            deployed)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>recentlyCachedOrDeployedFiles</varname></entry>

            <entry>New files in all repositories (cached or deployed)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>recentlyCachedArtifacts</varname></entry>

            <entry>New cached artifacts in all repositories</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>recentlyCachedFiles</varname></entry>

            <entry>New cached files in all repositories</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>recentlyDeployedArtifacts</varname></entry>

            <entry>New deployed artifacts in all repositories</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>recentlyDeployedFiles</varname></entry>

            <entry>New deployed files in all repositories</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>recentlyChangedArtifacts</varname></entry>

            <entry>Changed artifacts in all repositories</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>recentlyChangedFiles</varname></entry>

            <entry>Changed files in all repositories</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>systemRepositoryStatusChanges</varname></entry>

            <entry>Automatic or User-initiated status changes (out-of-service
            and blocked proxies)</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><varname>systemChanges</varname></entry>

            <entry>Booting nexus, changing configuration, re-indexing, and
            rebuilding of attributes</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>

  <section id="using-sect-browsing-log">
    <title>Log Files and Configuration</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus logs</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus administration</primary>

        <secondary>log files</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus administration</primary>

        <secondary>log configuration</secondary>
      </indexterm>The Logs and Config Files link is only visible to
    Administrative users under the Views menu. Click on this option brings up
    the dialog shown in <xref linkend="fig-nexus-logs" />. From this screen
    you can view the following log and configuration files by clicking on the
    drop down selection next to the Download button.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><filename>nexus.log</filename></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Think of this as the general application log for Nexus. Unless
          you are an administrative user, you might not have must interest in
          the information in this log. If you are trying to debug an error, or
          if you have uncovered a bug in Nexus, you'll use this log viewer to
          diagnose problems with Nexus.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><filename>nexus.xml</filename></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This XML file contains most of the configuration data for your
          instance of Nexus. It is stored in
          <filename>\${NEXUS_HOME}/runtime/apps/nexus/conf/nexus.xml</filename>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><filename>log4j.properties</filename></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This file controls the logging facility of Nexus using the
          standard Log4J property file syntax. To edit the format or level of
          the Log4J logging, click on Log under the Administration menu. For
          more information about configuring the Nexus Log, see <xref
          linkend="configuring-sect-log" />.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><filename>security.xml</filename></term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This XML file contains the configuration for the
          XmlAuthenticatingRealm and the XmlAuthorizingRealm. It contains
          built-in user definitions and any externally mapped users that are
          mapped to Nexus roles.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <figure id="fig-nexus-logs">
      <title>Browsing Nexus Logs and Configuration</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/repository-manager_log-file.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/repository-manager_log-file.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If you are running Nexus Professional, you should see a few more
    configuration files in this directory which will correspond to the
    Procurement and Staging suites. The configuration files specific to Nexus
    Professional are:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>procurement.xml</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This file contains the configuration for the Nexus Procurement
          Suite as described in <xref linkend="procure" />.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>staging.xml</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>This file contains the configuration for the Staging Suite as
          described in <xref linkend="staging" />.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>In <xref linkend="fig-nexus-logs" /> there is a "tail" checkbox. If
    this box is checked, then Nexus will always show you the end of a log
    file. This can come in handy if you want to see a continuously updated log
    file. When this tail box is checked, a dropdown at the bottom of the panel
    allows you to set the update frequency. The contents of this dropdown are
    shown in <xref linkend="fig-using-update-freq" />. If an update interval
    is selected, Nexus will periodically refresh the selected log file.</para>

    <figure id="fig-using-update-freq">
      <title>Selecting the Update Frequency when Tailing a Log File</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/using_tail-frequency.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/using_tail-frequency.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="using-sect-changing-password">
    <title>Changing Your Password</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>changing a password</primary>
      </indexterm>If you have the appropriate security privilege, you will see
    an option to change your password in the left-hand side of the browser. To
    change your password, click on change password, supply your current
    password, and choose a new password. When you click on Change Password,
    your Nexus password will be changed.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Changing Your Nexus Password</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/repository-manager_change-password.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/repository-manager_change-password.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="using-sect-problem-report">
    <title>Filing a Problem Report</title>

    <para>If you encounter a problem with Nexus, you can use the Nexus UI to
    report a bug or file an issue against the Nexus project in Sonatype's JIRA
    instance. To file a problem report, you will first need to sign up for an
    account on <ulink
    url="http://issues.sonatype.org">http://issues.sonatype.org</ulink>. In
    Nexus 1.6, you can click on "File Issue" in the Nexus menu, supply your
    Sonatype JIRA credentials, and file a problem report. Supply your JIRA
    username and password along with a short title and a description as shown
    in the following figure. When you file a Nexus problem report, Nexus will
    create a new issue in JIRA and attach your configuration and logs to the
    newly filed issue.</para>

    <figure id="fig-generate-report">
      <title>Generating a Nexus Problem Report</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/configuring-generate-report.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/configuring-generate-report.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</chapter>
