<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="maven">
  <title>Configuring Maven to Use Nexus</title>

  <section id="maven-sect-conf-maven-nexus">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

        <secondary>configuring repository mirrors</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

        <secondary>settings for Nexus</secondary>
      </indexterm>To use Nexus, you will configure Maven to check Nexus
    instead of the public repositories. To do this, you'll need to edit your
    mirror settings in your <filename>~/.m2/settings.xml</filename> file.
    First, we're going to demonstrate how to configure Maven to consult your
    Nexus installation instead of retrieving artifacts directly from the
    Central Maven repository. After we override the central repository and
    demonstrate that Nexus is working, we'll circle back to provide a more
    sensible set of settings that will cover both releases and
    snapshots.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="maven-sect-single-group">
    <title>Configuring Maven to Use a Single Nexus Group</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

        <secondary>settings for Nexus</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Apache Maven</primary>

        <secondary>settings.xml</secondary>
      </indexterm>If you are adopting Nexus for internal development you
    should configure a single Nexus group which contains both releases and
    snapshots. To do this, add snapshot repositories to your public group, and
    add the following mirror configuration to your Maven settings in
    <filename>~/.m2/settings.xml</filename>.</para>

    <example id="ex-maven-nexus-simple">
      <title>Configuring Maven to Use a Single Nexus Group</title>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;settings&gt;
  &lt;mirrors&gt;
    &lt;mirror&gt;
      &lt;!--This sends everything else to /public --&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;nexus&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;mirrorOf&gt;*&lt;/mirrorOf&gt;
      &lt;url&gt;http://localhost:8081/nexus/content/groups/public&lt;/url&gt;
    &lt;/mirror&gt;
  &lt;/mirrors&gt;
  &lt;profiles&gt;
    &lt;profile&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;nexus&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;!--Enable snapshots for the built in central repo to direct --&gt;
      &lt;!--all requests to nexus via the mirror --&gt;
      &lt;repositories&gt;
        &lt;repository&gt;
          &lt;id&gt;central&lt;/id&gt;
          &lt;url&gt;http://central&lt;/url&gt;
          &lt;releases&gt;&lt;enabled&gt;true&lt;/enabled&gt;&lt;/releases&gt;
          &lt;snapshots&gt;&lt;enabled&gt;true&lt;/enabled&gt;&lt;/snapshots&gt;
        &lt;/repository&gt;
      &lt;/repositories&gt;
     &lt;pluginRepositories&gt;
        &lt;pluginRepository&gt;
          &lt;id&gt;central&lt;/id&gt;
          &lt;url&gt;http://central&lt;/url&gt;
          &lt;releases&gt;&lt;enabled&gt;true&lt;/enabled&gt;&lt;/releases&gt;
          &lt;snapshots&gt;&lt;enabled&gt;true&lt;/enabled&gt;&lt;/snapshots&gt;
        &lt;/pluginRepository&gt;
      &lt;/pluginRepositories&gt;
    &lt;/profile&gt;
  &lt;/profiles&gt;
  &lt;activeProfiles&gt;
    &lt;!--make the profile active all the time --&gt;
    &lt;activeProfile&gt;nexus&lt;/activeProfile&gt;
  &lt;/activeProfiles&gt;
&lt;/settings&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>In <xref linkend="ex-maven-nexus-simple" /> we have defined a
      single profile: <varname>nexus</varname>. The <varname>nexus</varname>
      profile is configured to download from the central repository with a
      bogus <acronym>URL</acronym> of <varname>http://central</varname>. This
      <acronym>URL</acronym> is overridden by the mirror setting in the same
      <filename>settings.xml</filename> file to point to the URL of your
      single Nexus group. The <varname>nexus</varname> group is then listed as
      an active profile in the <sgmltag>activeProfiles</sgmltag>
      element.</para>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section id="maven-sect-custom-for-missing">
    <title>Adding Custom Repositories for Missing Dependencies</title>

    <para>If you've configured your Maven <filename>settings.xml</filename> to
    list Nexus as a mirror for all repositories, you might encounter projects
    which are unable to retrieve artifacts from your local Nexus installation.
    This usually happens because you are trying to build a project which has
    defined a custom set of <varname>repositories</varname> and
    <varname>snapshotRepositories</varname> in a <filename>pom.xml</filename>.
    This is definitely going to happen if you are building open source
    projects or if you've added custom third-party Maven repositories to your
    configuration.</para>

    <para>As an example, let's try to build Apache Shindig from source we've
    checked out of the Apache Incubator. What is Apache Shindig? It doesn't
    matter to this example; all we need is an example project we can easily
    checkout from source control and build. If you really want to know,
    Shindig is a project in the Apache Incubator that revolves around the
    OpenSocial API from Google. Shindig aims to provide a container that will
    allow people to execute OpenSocial gadgets. It provides us with an
    interesting example project, because it depends on some custom Maven
    repositories for components which have yet to be added to the Central
    Maven repository. Using Shindig we can show you what happens when Nexus
    doesn't have your artifacts and what steps you can take to add
    repositories to Nexus.</para>

    <para>The following example assumes that you have Subversion installed and
    that you are running Subversion from the command-line. Let's checkout
    Apache Shindig from the Apache Incubator with Subversion and attempt to
    build it from source. To do this, execute the following commands:</para>

    <screen>$ <command>svn co http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/incubator/shindig/trunk shindig</command>
... Subversion will checkout the trunk of Apache Shindig ...
$ <command>cd shindig</command>
$ <command>mvn install</command>
... Maven will build Shindig ...
Downloading: http://localhost:8081/nexus/content/groups/\
public/caja/caja/r2178/caja-r2178.jar
...
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[ERROR] BUILD ERROR
[INFO] ------------------------------------------------------------------------
[INFO] Failed to resolve artifact.

Missing:
----------
1) caja:caja:jar:r2178

  Try downloading the file manually from the project website.

...
----------
3 required artifacts are missing.

for artifact: 
  org.apache.shindig:shindig-gadgets:jar:1-SNAPSHOT

from the specified remote repositories:
  nexus (http://localhost:8081/nexus/content/groups/public)
</screen>

    <para>The build fails because it is unable to download three artifacts.
    One of the artifacts Maven was trying to download has a group identifier
    of <varname>caja</varname>, and artifactId of <varname>caja</varname>, and
    a version of <varname>r2178</varname>. It is an artifact that is hosted on
    a custom repository <ulink
    url="http://google-caja.googlecode.com/svn/maven">http://google-caja.googlecode.com/svn/maven</ulink>.
    Maven failed to download this artifact because your
    <filename>settings.xml</filename> was configured to direct all mirrors to
    the <varname>public</varname> and <varname>public-snapshots</varname>
    groups hosted on our Nexus installation. Even though the
    <filename>pom.xml</filename> for Apache Shindig defined a repository and
    pointed it at <ulink
    url="http://google-caja.googlecode.com/svn/maven">http://google-caja.googlecode.com/svn/maven</ulink>,
    Nexus won't retrieve an artifact from a repository it doesn't know about
    and you've configured all requests for remote artifacts to pass through
    Nexus. In fact, there are two repositories that Nexus doesn't know about
    in this build: <varname>caja</varname> and <varname>oauth</varname>.
    <ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/google-caja/">Caja</ulink> and <ulink
    url="http://code.google.com/p/oauth/">OAuth</ulink> are two libraries
    which are still in development. Both projects have been "released", and
    the versions that Shindig depends upon are certainly not SNAPSHOT
    releases, but these projects have not been published to the Central Maven
    Repository. We need to find a way to let Nexus know about these
    repositories before we can build this project.</para>

    <para>There are two ways to fix this problem. First, you can change your
    <filename>settings.xml</filename> to override specific repository
    identifiers. Instead of listing the Nexus public group as a
    <sgmltag>mirrorOf</sgmltag> all repositories, you could change the
    <sgmltag>mirrorOf</sgmltag> element in your
    <filename>settings.xml</filename> to "central". If you did this, Maven
    would then attempt to download the dependencies directly from the
    <varname>oauth</varname> and <varname>caja</varname> repositories at the
    <acronym>URL</acronym>s listed in the previous screen listing. This would
    work because Maven is only going to consult Nexus for repositories which
    match the repositories specified in the <sgmltag>mirrorOf</sgmltag>
    element in <filename>settings.xml</filename>. If Maven sees the
    repositories identifier <varname>caja</varname> or
    <varname>oauth</varname>, and doesn't see a mirror configured in your
    <filename>settings.xml</filename>, it is going to attempt to connect to
    the repository directly.</para>

    <para>The second, more interesting option is to add both of these
    repositories to Nexus and then add these repositories to the public
    group.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="maven-sect-adding">
    <title>Adding a New Repository</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Repository</primary>

        <secondary>creating</secondary>
      </indexterm>To add the caja repository, log into Nexus as an
    Administrator, and click on the Repositories link in the left-hand
    navigation menu in the Views/Repositories section. Clicking on this link
    should bring up a window that lists all of the repositories which Nexus
    knows about. You'll then want to create a new proxy repository. To do
    this, click on the Add link that is directly above the list of
    repositories. When you click the Add button, click the down arrow directly
    to the right of the word Add, this will show a drop-down which has the
    options: Hosted Repository, Proxy Repository, Virtual Repository, and
    Repository Group. Since you are creating a proxy repository, click on
    <indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Repository</primary>

        <secondary>create a proxy repository</secondary>
      </indexterm>Proxy Repository.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Creating a New Nexus Proxy Repository</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/repository-manager_add-repository-dropdown.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/repository-manager_add-repository-dropdown.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>Once you do this, you will see a screen resembling <xref
    linkend="fig-add-repo" />. Populate the required fields Repository ID and
    the Repository Name with "caja" and "Google Caja". Set the Repository
    Policy to "Release", and the Remote Storage Location to <ulink
    url="http://google-caja.googlecode.com/svn/maven">http://google-caja.googlecode.com/svn/maven</ulink>.</para>

    <figure id="fig-add-repo">
      <title>Adding a Nexus Repository</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/repository-manager_add-repository.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/repository-manager_add-repository.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>Once you've filled out this screen, click on the
    <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button. Nexus will then be configured with the
    caja proxy repository. Do the same thing for the oauth repository. Create
    a repository with the Repository ID of oauth, with a Release policy, and
    the Remote Storage Location of <ulink
    url="http://oauth.googlecode.com/svn/code/maven">http://oauth.googlecode.com/svn/code/maven</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="maven-sect-adding-to-group">
    <title>Adding a Repository to a Group</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus Repository Group</primary>

        <secondary>adding a repository</secondary>
      </indexterm>Next you will need to add both of these new repositories to
    the public Nexus Group. To do this, click on the Repositories link in the
    left-hand navigation menu in the Views/Repositories section. Nexus lists
    Groups and Repositories in the same list so click on the public group.
    After clicking on the public group, you should see the Browse and
    Configuration tabs in the lower half of the Nexus window.</para>

    <note>
      <para>If you click on a repository or a group in the Repositories list
      and you do not see the Configuration tab, this is because your Nexus
      user does not have administrative privileges. To perform the
      configuration tasks outlined in this chapter, you will need to be logged
      in as a user with administrative privileges.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Clicking on the Configuration tab will bring up a screen which looks
    like <xref linkend="fig-add-to-group" />.</para>

    <figure id="fig-add-to-group">
      <title>Adding New Repositories to a Nexus Group</title>

      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/repository-manager_add-to-group.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/repository-manager_add-to-group.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>To add the two new repositories to the <varname>public</varname>
    Nexus Group, find the repositories in the Available Repositories list on
    the right, click on the repository you want to add and drag it to the left
    to the Ordered Group Repositories list. Once the repository is in the
    Ordered Group Repositories list you can click and drag the repository
    within that list to alter the order in which a repository will be searched
    for a matching artifact. Once the Google Caja and Google OAuth project
    repositories are added to the public Nexus Group, you should be able to
    build Apache Shindig and watch Maven download the Caja and OAuth artifacts
    from the respective repositories.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Nexus makes use of an interesting Javascript widget library named
      <ulink url="http://extjs.com/">ExtJS</ulink>. ExtJS provides for a
      number of interesting UI widgets that allow for rich interaction like
      the drag-drop UI for adding repositories to a group and reordering the
      contents of a group.</para>
    </note>

    <para>In the last few sections, you encountered a situation where you
    needed to add two custom repositories to a build in order to download two
    libraries (Google Caja and Google OAuth) which are not available in the
    central Maven repository. If you were not using a repository manager, you
    would have added these repositories to the repository element of your
    project's <acronym>POM</acronym>, or you would have asked all of your
    developers to modify <filename>~/.m2/settings.xml</filename> to reference
    two new repositories. Instead, you used the Nexus repository manager to
    add the two repositories to the public group. If all of the developers are
    configured to point to the public group in Nexus, you can freely swap in
    new repositories without asking your developers to change local
    configuration, and you've gained a certain amount of control over which
    repositories are made available to your development team.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
