<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.discursive.com/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="plugins">
  <title>Nexus Plugins</title>

  <section id="plugins-sect-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus plugin</primary>

        <secondary>introduction</secondary>
      </indexterm>While Nexus is a capable repository management and
    collaboration platform without any plugin extensions, Sonatype has provide
    a way for developers to extend the feature set of Nexus by exposing a
    plugin API. This chapter is a brief survey of some of the plugins which
    are available for Nexus.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="plugins-sect-install">
    <title>Installing Plugins</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>plugin installation</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus plugin</primary>

        <secondary>installation of</secondary>
      </indexterm>Nexus plugins are incredibly easy to install. All you need
    to do to install a Nexus plugin is to put the Plugin JAR file in
    <filename>\${SONATYPE_WORK}/nexus/plugin-repository</filename>. As long as
    the plugin JAR is in the classpath of Nexus, it will be loaded the next
    time Nexus starts.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="plugins-sect-available">
    <title>Available Plugins</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus plugin</primary>

        <secondary>available plugins</secondary>
      </indexterm>The following sections list some of the available plugins.
    Some of the plugins in this list are very simple, like the Google
    Analytics Plugin. Other plugins such as the Staging Suite and Procurement
    Suite are of sufficient complexity to deserve an entire chapter of
    documentation.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Nexus Staging Suite</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>staging</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus plugin</primary>

          <secondary>staging plugin</secondary>
        </indexterm>The Nexus Staging Suite provides an organization with an
      easy way to deploy artifacts to a temporary staging repository prior to
      a full releases. Using the features in the Nexus Staging Suite,
      developers deploy to a hosted repository only to have the deployed
      artifacts intercepted by a staging profile and held in a temporary
      staging repository. Once artifacts have been deployed to a temporary
      staging repository, Nexus administrators, release engineers, and QA
      personnel can then validate and certify a set of staged artifact before
      they are either promoted to a hosted repository or discarded.</para>

      <para>The Nexus Staging Suite is an essential tool for organizations
      that need to incorporate QA into the release cycle. For more information
      about the Nexus Staging Suite, see <xref linkend="staging" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="plugins-sect-procurement">
      <title>Nexus Procurement Suite</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus plugin</primary>

          <secondary>procurement plugin</secondary>
        </indexterm>Many organizations want to have some control over the
      third-party dependencies used in a system. This could be for a number of
      reasons. Maybe an architecture groups wants to limit access to a set of
      approved frameworks, or maybe the product's legal team wants to make
      sure that the licenses of every open source library incorporated into a
      project has gone through some evaluation process. Whatever the reason,
      the Nexus Procurement Suite gives a Nexus Administrator some control
      over what artifacts are going to be made available from a proxied
      repository.</para>

      <para>The Nexus Procurement Suite gives organizations some control over
      inbound, third-party Maven artifacts. If you need to control and specify
      which dependencies are allow in your organization, you should learn
      about the Maven Procurement Plugin introduced in <xref
      linkend="procure" />.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="plugins-sect-ldap">
      <title>LDAP Authentication</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>LDAP integration</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus plugin</primary>

          <secondary>LDAP plugin</secondary>
        </indexterm>When an organization needs to integrate Nexus with LDAP,
      it can do so by installing the LDAP Authentication plugin. This plugin
      adds the necessary configuration panels and modifies the security
      subsystem of Nexus to delegate authentication and access control to an
      external LDAP server. You can configure Nexus roles to match roles for
      users in LDAP and use these roles to manage access to Nexus
      resources.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="plugins-sect-google">
      <title>Google Analytics Plugin</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Google analytics</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus plugin</primary>

          <secondary>Google analytics plugins</secondary>
        </indexterm>The Google Analytics Plugin is a simple plugin that simply
      inserts the Google Analytics tracking code just before the closing body
      tag in the Nexus HTML. To configure the Google Analytics plugin, you
      will need to put your organization's Google Analytics Web Property ID in
      the <filename>\${SONATYPE_WORK}/nexus/conf/ga-tracker-id.txt</filename>
      file.</para>

      <para>If the \${SONATYPE_WORK}/nexus/conf/ga-tracking-id.txt file
      contains the value "UA-16932923-9", then the Nexus markup should contain
      the following HTML just before the closing body tag:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Output from the Google Analytics Nexus Plugin</title>

        <programlisting>....

&lt;!-- Plugin post-BODY contributions start here --&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;
  var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? 
                     "https://ssl." : "http://www.");
  document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + 
                 gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' " + 
                 "type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E"));
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;
  var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-1693297-9");
  pageTracker._trackPageview();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;!-- Plugin post-BODY contributions ends here --&gt;

&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
