<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.discursive.com/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="procure">
  <chapterinfo>
    <date>${release.date}</date>

    <subjectset>
      <subject>
        <subjectterm>commercial</subjectterm>
      </subject>
    </subjectset>
  </chapterinfo>

  <title>Nexus Procurement Suite</title>

  <section id="procure-sect-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>procurement</primary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus plugin</primary>

        <secondary>procurement plugin</secondary>
      </indexterm>Nexus Procurement Suite provides an organization with
    control over what artifacts are allowed into a repository from an
    external, proxied repository such as the <indexterm>
        <primary>public repository</primary>

        <secondary>Maven Central</secondary>
      </indexterm>Maven Central Repository. Such control can be a prerequisite
    for organizations unwilling or unable to trust the entire contents of an
    external public repository. If an organization is developing mission
    critical code, they will likely want to subject every third party
    dependency to intense scrutiny and testing before making an artifact
    available to build a release or support a team of developers. In most
    Enterprise development environments, a developer can't just decide to add
    in a new dependency to Hibernate or to the Spring Framework on a whim; the
    decision to add dependencies to third-party libraries will need to be
    funneled through an oversight process that relies on an architect or an
    administrator to promote artifacts to a certified release
    repository.</para>

    <para>Another, more common experience is an organization which needs to
    proxy something like the Maven Central Repository but wants to limit
    access to specific versions of artifacts or prevent dependencies on
    everything contained under a specific group. Some organizations are more
    amenable to trusting the contents of a remote, proxied repository like
    Central, but they also need the ability to block certain dependencies.
    Maybe you work on a team that needs to limit access to dependencies with a
    certain license, or maybe you just want to make sure no one uses a
    problematic version of Hibernate with a known bug? The procurement suite
    is the tool that provides for both coarse and fine-grained control of the
    artifacts that can appear in a repository.</para>

    <section id="procure-sect-stages">
      <title>The Stages of Procurement</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement</primary>

          <secondary>stages of</secondary>
        </indexterm>A procured repository is a Hosted Repository which
      procures artifacts from a Proxy Repository. For example, one could
      create a hosted repository named "Secured Maven Central" and then
      configure this hosted repository to procure artifacts from the "Maven
      Central" repository. Once the hosted repository has been created and the
      source of procurement has been configured, the repository will obtain
      artifacts from the proxy repository as long as procurement is activated.
      If you start procurement for a Hosted repository, the hosted repository
      will fetch artifacts from the Proxy repository specified in the
      procurement settings. If you stop procurement for a Hosted Repository,
      no additional artifacts will be retrieved from the Proxy repository
      specified in the procurement settings.</para>

      <para>The ability to enable or disable procurement for a Hosted
      repository comes in very handy when you want to "certify" a Hosted
      repository as containing all of the artifacts (no more and no less)
      required for a production build. You can start procurement, run a build
      which triggers artifact procurement, and then stop procurement knowing
      that the procured repository now contains all of the artifacts required
      for building a specific project. Stopping procurement assures you that
      the contents of the repository will not change if the third-party,
      external proxied repository does. This is an extra level of assurance
      that your release artifacts depend on a set of artifacts under your
      complete control.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="procure-sect-approaches">
      <title>Two Approaches to Procurement</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement</primary>

          <secondary>approaches to</secondary>
        </indexterm>There are two main use cases for the Procurement Suite. In
      the first use case, the Procured Release Repository, the Procurement
      features of Nexus Professional are used to create a procured release
      repository to make sure that the organization has full control over the
      artifacts that are making it into a production release. The other use
      case, the Procured Development Repository, is for organizations that
      need more upfront control over which artifacts are allowed during the
      development of a project. The following sections describe these two uses
      cases in more detail.</para>

      <section id="procure-sect-cert">
        <title>Procured Release Repository</title>

        <para><indexterm>
            <primary>procurement</primary>

            <secondary>procured release repository</secondary>
          </indexterm>The Procurement Suite can be used in two different ways.
        In the "Procured Release" mode, developers work with a proxied 3rd
        party repository exactly as they would without the Procurement Suite.
        When a developer needs to add a dependency on a new artifact, Nexus
        will retrieve the artifact from the third-party repository (like
        Central or Apache Snapshots) and this artifact will be served to Maven
        via a proxied Nexus repository. When a QA or Release engineer needs to
        build a release or staging artifact, the Release or QA build would be
        configured to execute against a procured repository. A procured
        repository is one which only serves the artifacts which have been
        explicitly approved using the Procurement Suite.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Procurement to a Certified Release Repository</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="web">
              <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procurement_release-procurement.png" />
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="print">
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="figs/print/procurement_release-procurement.pdf"
                         scalefit="0" width="100%" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>In this model, developers can add as many third-party
        dependencies as they want, and it is the responsibility of the QA and
        Release engineers to approve (or procure) artifacts from the
        Development Repository to the QA/Release Repository. Developers can
        move forward, adding dependencies freely from a third-party, proxied
        repository, but once it is time to populate a Release repository, a
        Nexus administrator can audit the required artifacts, create a hosted
        repository, turn on procurement, populate the repository, and then
        deactivate procurement. This has the effect of "locking down" the
        artifacts that are involved in a production release.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="procure-sect-dev">
        <title>Procured Development Repository</title>

        <para><indexterm>
            <primary>procurement</primary>

            <secondary>procured development repository</secondary>
          </indexterm>There are some development environments which require
        even more control over which artifacts can be used and referenced by
        developers. In these situations, it might make sense to only allow
        developers to work with a procured repository. In this mode, a
        developer must ask a Nexus administrator for permission to add a
        dependency on a particular third-party artifact. A Procurement Manager
        would then have to approve the artifact, or group of artifacts so that
        they would be made available to the developers. This is the
        "ask-first" model for organizations that want to control which
        artifacts make it into the development cycle.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Procurement to a Certified Development Repository</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="web">
              <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procurement_ask-first-procurement.png" />
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="print">
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="figs/print/procurement_ask-first-procurement.pdf"
                         scalefit="0" width="100%" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>This is a model common in industries that have strict oversight
        requirements. More often than not, banks, hospitals, and government
        agencies have fairly strict regulations on the software that can be
        used by large development teams. With the Procured Development
        Repository approach, an architecture group can have full control over
        what artifacts can be referenced by a large development team.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="procure-sect-install">
    <title>Installing the Procurement Suite</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>procurement</primary>

        <secondary>installing plugin</secondary>
      </indexterm>If you installed Nexus Professional, the Nexus Procurement
    Suite is already installed. Just start Nexus and look for the Artifact
    Procurement option in the left-hand navigation menu of the Nexus
    interface. If you see the Artifact Procurement link as shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-procure-links" />, the Procurement Suite is available and
    ready to be configured.</para>

    <figure id="fig-procure-links">
      <title>Artifact Procurement in the Nexus Menu</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="web">
          <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procurement_installation.png" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="print">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="figs/print/procurement_installation.pdf"
                     scalefit="0" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="procure-sect-configure">
    <title>Setting up a Procured Repository</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus repository</primary>

        <secondary>procured repository</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>procurement</primary>

        <secondary>creating procured repository</secondary>
      </indexterm>This section will walk through the process of creating and
    configuring a hosted repository named "Procured Central" which will be
    procured from the "Maven Central" proxy repository. Setting up a procured
    repository consists of the following steps:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Enabling Remote Index Downloads for a Proxy Repository</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Creating a Hosted Repository to be Procured</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Configuring Procurement for the Hosted Repository</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Configuring Procurement Rules</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Before configuring a procured repository, you need to make sure that
    you have enabled Remote Index downloading for the proxied repository that
    will serve as the source for your procured repository.</para>

    <note>
      <para>If you are attempting to procure artifacts from a remote
      repository which does not have a repository index, you can still use the
      procurement suite. Without a remote repository index, you will need to
      configure procurement rules manually without the benefit of the already
      populated repository tree shown in <xref
      linkend="procure-sect-config-rule" />.</para>
    </note>

    <section id="procure-sect-enabled-remote">
      <title>Enable Remote Index Downloads</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus repository</primary>

          <secondary>proxy repository</secondary>

          <tertiary>remote index</tertiary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement</primary>

          <secondary>remote index</secondary>
        </indexterm>When you configure procurement rules for a hosted
      repository, the administrative interface displays the repository as a
      tree of groups and artifacts populated from the Remote Repository's
      Nexus Index. Nexus ships with a set of proxy repositories, but remote
      index downloading is disabled by default. To use procurement, you will
      need to tell Nexus to download the remote indexes for a proxy
      repository. Click on "Repositories" under Views/Repositories in the
      Nexus menu, then click on the Maven Central repository in the list of
      repositories. Click on the Configuration tab, locate Download Remote
      Indexes, and switch this option to "True" as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-procure-enabling-remote" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-enabling-remote">
        <title>Enabling Remote Index Downloads for a Proxy Repository</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_central-download-remote-index.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_central-download-remote-index.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Click on the Save button in the dialog shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-procure-enabling-remote" />. Right-click on the Index in
      the Repositories list and select "Re-Index". Nexus will then download
      the remote repository and recreate the index for any Repository Groups
      that contain this proxied repository. Nexus may take a few minutes to
      download the remote index for a large repository. Depending on your
      connection to the Internet, this process can take anywhere from under a
      minute to a few minutes. The size of the remote index for Maven Central
      is on the order of 30 MB. To check on the status of the remote index
      download, click on System Feeds under Views in the Nexus menu. Click on
      the last feed to see a list of "System Changes in Nexus". If you see a
      log entry like the one highlighted in <xref
      linkend="fig-procure-system-feed" />, Nexus has successfully downloaded
      the Remote Index from Maven Central.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-system-feed">
        <title>Verification that the Remote Index has been Downloaded</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_reindex-system-feed.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_reindex-system-feed.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="procue-sect-create-hosted">
      <title>Create a Hosted Repository</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>Nexus repository</primary>

          <secondary>hosted repository</secondary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement</primary>

          <secondary>hosted repository</secondary>
        </indexterm>When you configure procurement you are establishing a
      relationship between a Proxy repository and a Hosted repository. To
      create a Hosted repository, select Repositories from the Administration
      section of the Nexus menu, and click on the Add button selecting Hosted
      as shown in <xref linkend="fig-procure-add-hosted" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-add-hosted">
        <title>Adding a Hosted Repository</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_add-hosted.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_add-hosted.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Selecting Hosted will then load the Repository Config form shown
      in <xref linkend="fig-procure-add-secured" />. Create a repository with
      a Repository ID of "secured" and a name of "Secured". Make the release
      policy "Release". Click the <guibutton>Save</guibutton> button to create
      the new Hosted Repository.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-add-secured">
        <title>Adding the "Secured" Hosted Repository</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_after-add-secured.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_after-add-secured.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="procure-sect-config-procure-hosted">
      <title>Configuring Procurement for Hosted Repository</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement</primary>

          <secondary>hosted repository</secondary>
        </indexterm>At this point, the list of Repositories will have a new
      Hosted repository named "Secured". The next step is to start procurement
      for the new Secured repository. When you do this, you are establishing a
      relationship between the new Hosted repository and a Proxy repository.
      In this case, we're configuring procurement for the Secured repository
      and we're telling the Procurement Suite to procure artifacts from the
      Maven Central proxy repository. To configure this relationship and to
      start procurement, click on Artifact Procurement under the Enterprise
      menu. In the Procurement panel, click on Add Procurement Repository as
      shown in <xref linkend="fig-procure-starting-procurement" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-starting-procurement">
        <title>Adding a Procured Repository</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_add-procured-repository.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_add-procured-repository.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement</primary>

          <secondary>source repository</secondary>
        </indexterm>You will then be presented with the Start Procurement
      dialog as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-procure-start-procurement-dialog" />. Select the "Maven
      Central" proxy repository from the list of available Source
      repositories.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-start-procurement-dialog">
        <title>Configuring Procurement for a Hosted Repository</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_configure-procurement-confirm.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_configure-procurement-confirm.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Procurement is now configured and started, if you are using an
      instance of Nexus installed on localhost port 8081, you can configure
      your clients to reference the new Secured repository at <ulink
      url="http://localhost:8081/nexus/content/repositories/secured">http://localhost:8081/nexus/content/repositories/secured</ulink>.
      By default, all artifacts are denied and without further customization
      of the procurement rules no artifacts will be available in the new
      Secured repository.</para>

      <para>One interesting thing to note about the "Secured" repository is
      that the Repository Type changed, once procurement was started. When
      procurement is activate for a Hosted repository, the repository will
      show up in the Nexus interface as a Proxy repository. Click refresh in
      the Repositories list, and look at the Secured repository in the list of
      repositories, you will see that the repository type column contains
      "proxy" as shown in <xref linkend="fig-procure-hosted-now-proxy" />.
      When procurement is started for a hosted repository it is effectively a
      proxy repository, and when it is stopped it will revert back to being a
      normal hosted repository.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-hosted-now-proxy">
        <title>Hosted Repository is a Proxy Repository while Procurement is
        Active</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procured_started-now-proxy.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procured_started-now-proxy.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="procure-sect-creating-rules">
    <title>Procured Repository Administration</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>procurement</primary>

        <secondary>administration</secondary>
      </indexterm>Once you've defined the relationship between a Hosted
    repository and a Proxy repository and you have started procurement, you
    can start defining the rules which will control which artifacts are
    allowed in a procured repository and which artifacts are denied. You can
    also start and stop procurement. This section details some of the
    administration panels and features which are available for a procured
    repository.</para>

    <section id="procure-sect-viewing">
      <title>Viewing the Procurement Management Interface</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement</primary>

          <secondary>management interface</secondary>
        </indexterm>A procurement rule is a rule to allow or deny the
      procurement of a group, artifact, or a collection of groups or
      artifacts. You load the Artifact Procurement interface by selecting
      Artifact Procurement under the Enterprise section of the Nexus menu.
      Clicking on this link will load a list of procured repositories.
      Clicking on the repository will load the entire repository in a tree as
      shown in <xref linkend="fig-procure-repository-view" />. This section
      will illustrate the steps required for blocking access to an entire
      artifact and then selectively allowing access to a particular version of
      that same artifact. This is a common use-case in organizations which
      want to standardize on specific versions of a particular
      dependency.</para>

      <note>
        <para>If you are attempting to procure artifacts from a remote
        repository which does not have a repository index, you can still use
        the procurement suite. Without a remote repository index, you will
        need to configure procurement rules manually without the benefit of
        the already populated repository tree shown in this section.</para>
      </note>

      <figure id="fig-procure-repository-view">
        <title>Viewing a Repository in the Artifact Procurement
        Interface</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_repository-view.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_repository-view.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The directory tree in <xref
      linkend="fig-procure-repository-view" /> is the index of the proxy
      repository from which artifacts are being procured.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="procure-sect-config-rule" label="">
      <title>Configuring a Procurement Rule</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement rule</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement</primary>

          <secondary>configuring rules</secondary>
        </indexterm>To configure a procurement rule, right click on a folder
      in the tree. <xref linkend="fig-procure-deny-group-all" /> displays the
      procurement interface after right clicking on the jython artifact
      folder. In this dialog, we are telling the procurement interface to deny
      everything in the jython group and its sub-groups. If you attempt to
      retrieve any version under the jython artifact after this rule is
      created, the Procurement Suite will prevent access to this artifact. For
      example, if you attempt to build a project that depends on
      jython:jython:2.1, it will not be made available via the Secured
      repository created in <xref linkend="procure-sect-configure" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-deny-group-all">
        <title>Denying Procurement for Everything Under a Group</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_deny-all-jython.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_deny-all-jython.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>After denying access to the entire jython artifact, right-click on
      the 2.1 version folder under the jython artifact folder. Select "Exactly
      the artifact" as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-procure-allowing-artifact" /> to allow for the procurement
      of only the 2.1 version. This has the effect of creating a specific rule
      which allows the procurement of a single version of the jython:jython
      artifact.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-allowing-artifact">
        <title>Allowing Access to a Single Artifact in a Denied Group</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_approve-artifact.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_approve-artifact.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>After allowing this element, your procurement tree is going to
      contain red and green markers on the affected folders as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-procure-composite-effects" />. While the jython artifact
      folder has a red slash through it the 2.1 version folder has a green
      check. You have configured the Procurement Suite to deny access to all
      versions of the jython artifact except version 2.1.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-composite-effects">
        <title>Viewing the Effect of Composite Procurement Rules on the
        Tree</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_only-one-jython.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_only-one-jython.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="procure-sect-manage-rules">
      <title>Managing Procurement Rules</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement rules</primary>
        </indexterm><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement</primary>

          <secondary>configuring rules</secondary>
        </indexterm>Once you've created a set of procurement rules you are
      going to want to know how to view the procurement rules which are
      applicable to a particular node. Procurement rules will frequently
      overlap; for example, in <xref linkend="procure-sect-creating-rules" />,
      there are two rules: one rule applies to all of the versions (folder)
      below the jython artifact folder, and the other rule applies to a
      particular version directory. Since rules can overlap, Nexus provides a
      simple way to list and manage the rules which apply to a specific node
      in the directory tree. <xref linkend="fig-procure-composite-effects" />
      shows the resolved procurement rules after clicking on the Jython 2.1
      version artifact from <xref linkend="procure-sect-configure" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-effective">
        <title>Effective Procurement Rules for a Particular Node</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_effective-rules.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_effective-rules.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>This dialog gives the procurement administrator a fine-grained
      view into the rules that apply to a particular node. From this dialog
      you can remove rules which apply to a specific node.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="procure-sect-stopping">
      <title>Stopping Procurement</title>

      <para><indexterm>
          <primary>procurement</primary>

          <secondary>stopping</secondary>
        </indexterm>Some organizations may want to "lock down" the artifacts
      that a release build can depend upon, and it is also a good idea to make
      sure that your build isn't going to be affected by changes to a
      repository not under you control. A procurement administrator might
      configure a procured repository, start procurement, and run an
      enterprise build against the repository to populate the procured, hosted
      repository with all of the necessary artifacts. After this process, the
      procurement administrator can stop procurement and continue to run the
      same release build against the hosted repository which now contains all
      of the procured artifacts.</para>

      <para>To stop procurement, go to the Artifact Procurement management
      interface by clicking on Artifact Procurement under the Enterprise
      section of the Nexus menu. Right click on the repository and choose Stop
      Procurement as shown in <xref linkend="fig-procure-stopping" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-stopping">
        <title>Stopping Procurement for a Procured Repository</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_stop-procurement.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_stop-procurement.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>After choosing Stop Procurement, you will then see a dialog
      confirming your decision to stop procurement as shown in <xref
      linkend="fig-procure-stop-confirm" />.</para>

      <figure id="fig-procure-stop-confirm">
        <title>Stop Procurement Confirmation Dialog</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/procure_stop-procurement-confirm.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/procure_stop-procurement-confirm.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Once procurement is stopped, the Secure repository will revert
      back to being a plain-old Hosted repository. You can validate this by
      looking at the repository type in the list of repositories.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
