<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.sonatype.com/tmp/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introducing Sonatype Nexus</title>

  <section id="intro-sect-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Nexus manages software “artifacts” required for development,
    deployment, and provisioning. If you develop software, Nexus can help you
    share those artifacts with other developers and end-users. Maven’s central
    repository has always served as a great convenience for users of Maven,
    but it has always been recommended to maintain your own repositories to
    ensure stability within your organization. Nexus greatly simplifies the
    maintenance of your own internal repositories and access to external
    repositories. With Nexus you can completely control access to, and
    deployment of, every artifact in your organization from a single
    location.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Nexus Open Source</title>

    <para>Nexus Open Source provides you with an essential level of control
    over the external Maven repositories you use and the internal repositories
    you create. It provides infrastructure and services for organizations that
    use repository managers to obtain and deliver software. If you create
    software libraries or applications for your end-users, you can use Nexus
    Open Source to distribute your software. If your software depends upon
    open source software components, you can cache software artifacts from
    remote repositories.</para>

    <section id="intro-sect-open-features">
      <title>Nexus Open Source Features</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Hosting Repositories</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When you host a Maven repository with Nexus Open Source, you
            can upload artifacts using the Nexus interface, or you can deploy
            artifacts to hosted repositories using Maven. Nexus will also
            create the standard Nexus Index for all of your hosted
            repositories which will allow tools like m2eclipse to rapidly
            locate software artifacts for your developers.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Proxy Remote Repositories</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When you proxy a remote repository with Nexus Open source
            you can control all aspects of the connection to a remote
            repository including security parameters, HTTP proxy settings. You
            can configure which mirrors Nexus will download artifacts from,
            and you can control how long Nexus will store artifacts and how it
            will expire artifacts which are no longer referenced by your
            build.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Repository Groups</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Grouping repositories allows you to consolidate multiple
            repositories into a single URL. This makes configuring your
            development environment very easy. All of your developers can
            point to a single repository group URL, and if anyone ever needs a
            custom remote repository added to the group, you can do this in a
            central location without having to modify every developer’s
            workstation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Fine-grained Security Model</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Open Source ships with a very capable and customizable
            security model. Every operation in Nexus is associated with a
            privilege, and privileges can be combined into standard Nexus
            roles. Users can then be assigned both individual privileges and
            roles that can be applied globally or at a fine grained level. You
            can create custom administrative roles that limit certain
            repository actions such as deployment to specific groups of
            developers and you can use these security roles to model the
            structure of your organization.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Flexible LDAP Integration</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If your organization uses an LDAP server, Nexus Professional
            can integrate with an external authentication and access control
            system. Nexus Professional is smart enough to be able to
            automatically map LDAP groups to the appropriate Nexus roles, and
            it also provides a very flexible facility for mapping existing
            users and existing roles to Nexus roles.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Artifact Search</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Open Source provides an intuitive search feature which
            allows you to search for software artifacts by identifiers such as
            groupId, artifactId, version, classifier, and packaging, names of
            classes contained in Java archives, keywords, and artifact
            checksums. Nexus search makes use of the industry standard for
            repository indexes, the Nexus Index format, and Nexus will
            automatically download a Nexus index from all remote repositories
            which create a Nexus index. Nexus will also automatically expose a
            Nexus index for any hosted repositories you create.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Scheduled Services</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Open Source has the concept of scheduled services -
            periodic jobs which take care of various repository management
            tasks such as deleting old snapshots, evicting unused items, and
            publishing repository indexes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>REST Services</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Open Source is based on a series of REST services, and
            when you are using the Nexus web front-end UI, you are really just
            interacting with a set of REST service. Because of this open
            architecture, you can leverage the REST service to create custom
            interactions or to automate repository management with your own
            scripts.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Nexus Plugins</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Open Source provides a rich API for extension in the
            form of Nexus Plugins. When you write a Nexus Plugin, you can
            customize REST services, the Nexus UI, repository formats, or
            write components that can intercept requests and add new
            capabilities to the platform. The plugin API which you have access
            to in Nexus Open Source is the same plugin API that is used to
            implement value-added features available in Nexus
            Professional.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Integration with m2eclipse</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When you use Nexus as a repository manager it creates
            indexes that support some of the next-generation tools available
            in m2eclipse - Sonatype’s Maven plugin for the Eclipse IDE. If you
            publish new artifacts and archetypes to Nexus, they are
            immediately available to m2eclipse project creation wizards and
            are included in m2eclipse search results.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Nexus Open Source License</title>

      <para>Nexus Open Source is available under the GNU General Public
      License version 3 (GPLv3). The text of this license is available from
      the Open Source Initiative (OSI) here: <ulink
      url="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/gpl-3.0.html">http://www.opensource.org/licenses/gpl-3.0.html</ulink>.</para>

      <para>The Nexus Indexer is made available under the Eclipse Public
      License -v 1.0. The text of this license is available from the Open
      Source Initiative (OSI) here: <ulink
      url="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/eclipse-1.0.php">http://www.opensource.org/licenses/eclipse-1.0.php</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Nexus Professional</title>

    <para>Nexus Professional was designed to meet the needs of the enterprise.
    It is a central point of access to external repositories which provides
    the necessary controls to make sure that only approved artifacts enter
    into your software development environment. It is also a central
    distribution point with the intelligence required to support the decision
    that go into making quality software. The extensibility provided by the
    custom metadata plugin coupled with REST services only available in Nexus
    Professional also lay the foundation for highly complex interactions
    within the enterprise. Once you start to use the workflow and decision
    support features of Nexus Professional, you will start to see it as the
    “assembly line” - the central collaboration point for your software
    development efforts.</para>

    <section id="intro-sect-pro-features">
      <title>Nexus Professional Features</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Nexus Procurement Suite</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Consider the default behavior of a proxy repository. Any
            developer can reference any artifact stored in a remote repository
            and cause Nexus to retrieve the artifact from the remote
            repository and serve back to a developer. Very often a company
            might want to control the set of artifacts which can be referenced
            in a proxy repository. Maybe the company has unique security
            requirements which require every third-party library to be
            subjected to a rigorous security audit before they can used. Or,
            maybe another company has a legal team which needs to verify that
            every artifact referenced by your software adheres to an
            inflexible set of license guidelines. The Nexus Procurement Suite
            was design to give organization this level of control over the
            artifacts that can be served from Nexus.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Nexus Staging Suite</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When was the last time you did a software release to a
            production system? Did it involve a QA team that had to sign-off
            on a particular build? What was the process you used to redeploy a
            new build if QA found a problem with the system at the last
            minute? Because few organizations use a mature process to manage
            binary software artifacts, there is little in the way of
            infrastructure designed to keep track of the output of a build.
            The Nexus Staging Suite changes this by provide workflow support
            for binary software artifacts. If you need to create a release
            artifact and deploy it to a hosted repository, you can use the
            Staging Suite to post a collection of related, staged artifacts
            which can be tested, promoted, or discarded as a unit. Nexus keeps
            track of the individuals that are involved in a staged, managed
            release and can be used to support the decisions that go into
            producing quality software.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Hosting Project Web Sites</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Professional is a publishing destination for project
            web sites. While you very easily generate a project web site with
            Maven, without Nexus, you will need to set up a WebDAV server and
            configure both your web server and build with the appropriate
            security credentials. With Nexus, you can deploy your project’s
            web site to the same infrastructure that hosts the project’s build
            output. This single destination for binaries and documentation
            helps to minimize the number of moving parts in your development
            environment. You don’t have to worry about configuring another web
            server or configuring your builds to distribute the project site
            using a different protocol, you simple point your project at Nexus
            and deploy the project site.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Support for OSGi Repositories</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Instead of just supporting Maven repositories, Nexus
            Professional supports OSGi Bundle repositories and P2 repositories
            for those developers who are targetting OSGi or the Eclipse
            platform. Just like you can proxy, host, and group Maven
            repositories, Nexus Professional allows you to do the same with
            OSGi repositories.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Enterprise LDAP Support </term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Professional offers LDAP support features for
            enterprise LDAP deployments including detailed configuration of
            cache parameters, support for multiple LDAP servers and backup
            mirrors, the ability to test user logins, support for common
            user/group mapping templates, and the ability to support more than
            one schema across multiple servers.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Support for Atlassian Crowd</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If your organization uses Atlassian Crowd, Nexus
            Professional can delegate authentication and access control to a
            Crowd server and map Crowd groups to the appropriate Nexus
            roles.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>The User Account Plugin</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When you are running a large, public instance of Nexus, it
            is often very useful to allow users to sign up for an account
            without the assistance of an administrator. Nexus Professional’s
            User Account plugin allows for just this. With this plugin
            activate, a new user simply has to fill out a simple form and type
            in letters from a CAPTCHA. Once a user has signed up for Nexus,
            Nexus will then send an email with a validation link. If you are
            working in an environment with hundreds or thousand of users the
            user account plugin will allow you to support the tool without
            having to create logins for each individual user.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Maven Settings Management</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Professional along with the Nexus Maven Plugin allow
            you to manage Maven Settings. Once you have developed a Maven
            Settings template, developers can then connect to Nexus
            Professional using the Nexus Maven plugin which will take
            repsonsibility for downloading a Maven Settings file from Nexus
            and replacing the existing Maven Settings on a local
            workstation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Support for Artifact Bundles</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When software is deployed to the Central Maven repository,
            it is deployed as a signed artifact bundle. Nexus Professional’s
            Staging Suite allows you to upload artifact bundles to a staged
            repository.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Artifact Validation and Verification</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The software artifacts you download from a remote repository
            are often signed with PGP signatures. Nexus Professional will make
            sure that these PGP signature are valid and the procurement plugin
            defines a few other rules that can be applied to artifacts which
            are downloaded from remote repositories. Nexus Professional also
            defines an API which allows you to create your own custom
            verification rules.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Custom Repository Metadata</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Professional provides a facility for user-defined,
            custom metadata. If you need to keep track of custom attributes to
            support approval workflow or to associate custom identifiers with
            software artifacts, you can use Nexus to define and manipulate
            custom attributes which can be associated with artifacts in a
            Nexus repository.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Nexus Professional License</title>

      <para>Nexus Professional is made available under a commercial license
      for businesses. Is available for free for use in qualifying Open Source
      projects, and is available at a discount for select Non-profits.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="intro-sect-choosing">
    <title>Choosing a Nexus Edition</title>

    <para>If you are wondering which edition is appropriate for your
    organization. The following sections outline some reasons for choosing
    either Nexus Open Source of Nexus Professional.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Use Nexus Open Source...</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>...if you are new to Repository Management.</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you are new to repository management, you should pick up
            a copy of Nexus Open Source, and experiment with Hosted and Proxy
            repositories. You should get a sense of how Maven Settings are
            configured to retrieve artifacts from a single Repository Group,
            and you should download a copy of the free Nexus book - Repository
            Management with Nexus. Once you’ve familiarized yourself with
            Nexus Open Souce, you can easily upgrade to Nexus Professional by
            downloading and installing Nexus Professional. Nexus stores all of
            your repository data and configuration in a directory named
            sonatype-work which is separate from the Nexus application
            directory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>...if you are looking for more stability and control.</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you depend directly on public repositories such as the
            Central Maven repository or the various repositories maintained by
            organizations like Codehaus or the Apache Software Foundation, you
            rely on these servers to be available to your developers 100% of
            the time. If a public repository goes down for maintenance, so
            does your development process. With a local proxy of Maven
            artifacts, you buy yourself a stable, isolated build. Even if a
            public repositories becomes unavailable, you will still be able to
            build your software against artifacts cached in your own Nexus
            installation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>...if you need to manage internal software
          distribution.</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If your organization needs to support collaboration between
            internal teams, you can use Nexus to support the distribution of
            internal software. With Nexus, sharing components between internal
            groups is as easy as adding a dependency from Maven Central. Just
            publish a JAR to Nexus, configure the appropriate repositories
            groups and inform others in our organization of the Maven
            coordinates. Using a repository management doesn’t just make it
            easier to proxy external software artifacts, it makes it easier to
            share internal artifacts.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>...if you need an intelligent local proxy.</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Many developers run Nexus on a local workstation as a way to
            gain more control over the repositories used by Nexus. This is
            also a great way to start evaluating Nexus. Download and install
            Nexus on your local workstation and point your Maven settings at
            http://localhost:8081/nexus. When you need to add a new
            repository, all you need to do is change the configuration of your
            local Nexus installation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>...if you need to integrate with an LDAP server.</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you need to integrate Nexus with an an LDAP server,
            download Nexus Open Source. Nexus provides documented integration
            with popular LDAP servers such as OpenLDAP, Microsoft’s Active
            Directory Server, and any other directory product which implements
            the LDAP standard.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Use Nexus Professional...</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>...if you are looking for Professional Support.</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>When you purchase Nexus Professional, you are purchasing one
            year of support from the team that created the industry-standard
            in repository management. With Nexus Professional, you not only
            get a capable repository manager, you get the peace of mind that
            help is just a phone call away. Sonatype also offers an array of
            implementation and migration services for organizations looking
            for an extra level of assistance. Contact Sonatype Sales for more
            information, call +1 (888) 866-2836.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>...if you need a repository manager that can support release
          and quality assurance decisions.</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Professional’s Staging Suite can track the staatus of
            a software release and make sure that different decision makers
            are notified and supported during a software release. If you are
            looking for a repository manager that can automate and support
            software releases, download Nexus Professional and start learning
            about Staged repositories and Staging Rulesets. When you start
            using Nexus Professional, your operations, quality assurance, and
            development teams can use the repository manager as a central
            point of collaboration.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>...if you need more control over external artifacts.</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you need more control over which external artifacts can
            be referenced and used in internal projects, you will need to use
            the Nexus Procurement Suite which is a part of Nexus Professional.
            While repositories like Maven Central are a great convenience,
            allowing your developers carte blanche access to any external
            library is often unacceptable in today’s legal and regulatory
            environment. Nexus Professional’s Procurement Suite allows you to
            enforce standards for external libraries. If you want to ensure
            that every dependency is evalautated for security or license
            compliance, download Nexus Professional.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>...if you develop software for an Open Source project.</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Are you developing an open source project? If so, most open
            source projects qualify for a free Nexus Professional license.
            Open source projects can qualify for a free Professional license,
            or they can take advantage of free Nexus Professional hosting on
            http://oss.sonatype.org. Sonatype is very committed to supporting
            the development of quality open source and this is our way of
            giving back to the community.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>...if you are developing and deploying to OSGi
          platforms.</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you are developing OSGi components using OBR
            repositories, or if you are developing OSGi components using the
            P2 repository format, you will need to use the OSGi support
            available in the Nexus Professional distribution. Nexus
            Professional supports a wider array of repository formats than
            Nexus Open Source. As the industry moves toward OSGi as a
            standard, you should be using a product which supports these
            emerging standards as well as the existing repository formats used
            by millions of developers.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>...if you need to integrate with Enterprise-level Security
          (LDAP and Crowd).</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you need to integrate Nexus with an Atlassian Crowd
            server or an enterprise LDAP deployment involving multiple servers
            or multiple LDAP schemas, download Nexus Professional. While Nexus
            Open Source provides extension points for writing custom security
            realms, Nexus Professional provides solid LDAP and Crowd support
            for the large, mission-critical LDAP deployments. If you need to
            support LDAP failover and federation, use Nexus Professional.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Comparing Nexus Open Source and Nexus Professional
      Features</title>

      <para>The following table summarizes the differences between Nexus Open
      Source and Nexus Professional:</para>

      <figure id="fig-intro-open-v-pro">
        <title>Sonatype Nexus Feature Matrix</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="web" security="">
            <imagedata fileref="figs/web/nx-open-vs-pro-datasheet-4.png" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="print" security="">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figs/print/nx-open-vs-pro-datasheet-4.pdf"
                       scalefit="0" width="100%" wordsize="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="intro-sect-history">
    <title>History of Nexus</title>

    <para><indexterm>
        <primary>Nexus</primary>

        <secondary>history of</secondary>
      </indexterm><indexterm>
        <primary>Cservenak, Tamas</primary>
      </indexterm>Tamas Cservenak started working on <indexterm>
        <primary>Proximity</primary>
      </indexterm>Proximity in December 2005 as he was trying to find a way to
    isolate his own systems from an incredibly slow <acronym>ADSL</acronym>
    connection provided by a Hungarian <acronym>ISP</acronym>. Proximity
    started as a simple web application to proxy artifacts for a small
    organization with connectivity issues. Creating a local on-demand cache
    for Maven artifacts from the central Maven repository gave an organization
    access to the artifacts on the Central Maven Repository, but it also made
    sure that these artifacts weren't downloaded over a very slow
    <acronym>ADSL</acronym> connection used by a number of developers. In
    2007, <indexterm>
        <primary>Sonatype</primary>
      </indexterm>Sonatype asked Tamas to help create a similar product named
    Nexus. Nexus is currently considered the logical next step to Proximity.
    Nexus currently has an active development team, and portions of the
    indexing code from Nexus are also being used in <indexterm>
        <primary>m2eclipse</primary>
      </indexterm>m2eclipse.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
