<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.sonatype.com/tmp/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="foreword">
  <title>Foreword: ${project.version}</title>

  <para>This book covers both Nexus Open Source and Nexus Professional, a
  product which brings full control and visibility to organizations which
  depend on Maven repositories to manage releases and distribute software. You
  are encouraged to check <ulink
  url="http://books.sonatype.com/nexus-book">http://books.sonatype.com/nexus-book</ulink>
  weekly for any updates to the content.</para>

  <para>If you would like to receive updates whenever there is a change to
  this book, you can subscribe to our Book Announcement mailing list. To
  subscribe to this mailing list, send an email to: <ulink
  url="mailto:book-notify-subscribe@sonatype.org">book-notify-subscribe@sonatype.org</ulink></para>

  <para>We welcome your feedback, please do not hesitate to contact the
  Sonatype team with any questions or ideas you may have about the product.
  We're focused on making the adoption of Nexus Open Source and Nexus
  Professional painless, and we are here to do anything we can to help speed
  up the learning curve associated with some of the more advanced and powerful
  features of Nexus.</para>

  <para>If you have any feedback or questions, you are encouraged to post an
  item in our Get Satisfaction page for this book: <ulink
  url="http://www.getsatisfaction.com/sonatype/products/sonatype_repository_management_with_nexus">http://www.getsatisfaction.com/sonatype/products/sonatype_repository_management_with_nexus</ulink>.</para>

  <para>Tim O'Brien, Sonatype</para>

  <para>${release.month}, ${copyright.year}</para>

  <para>Edition: ${project.version}</para>

  <section>
    <title>Changes in Edition 3.0.1</title>

    <para>The following changes were made in 3.0.1:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Added New Section <xref linkend="using-dependencies" />.
        (NXBOOK-577)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added a step about setting to LANG to the post-install
        checklist. (NXBOOK-561)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changes in Edition 3.0</title>

    <para>The following changes were made in 3.0:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Added Anders Hammar as an author. (NXBOOK-577)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Upgrade Nexus version number fo 1.9.0.2. (NXBOOK-580)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Removed a section that was focused on providing upgrade
        instructions for users upgrading from Nexus 1.5 to Nexus 1.6.
        (NXBOOK-578)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Transitioned image generation tools from Photoshop-based Macros
        to a series of scripts using Imagemagick to scale and create book
        images. (NXBOOK-579 and NXBOOK-581)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Updated Sonatype's address to Maryland address.
        (NXBOOK-565)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Fixed a minor typo in <xref
        linkend="installation-sect-upgrading" />. (NXBOOK-499)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Removed instructions for upgrading Nexus 1.2 to Nexus 1.3 from
        <xref linkend="installation-sect-upgrading" />. (NXBOOK-583)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The following people helped improve the quality of Edition 3.0 by
    reporting typos, making suggestions, or contributing directly to the
    development of this book:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Trevor Harmon for reporting typos in NXBOOK-499.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</preface>
