<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.sonatype.com/tmp/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="foreword">
  <title>Foreword: ${project.version}</title>

  <para>This book covers both Nexus Open Source and Nexus Professional, a
  product which brings full control and visibility to organizations which
  depend on Maven repositories to manage releases and distribute software. You
  are encouraged to check <ulink
  url="http://books.sonatype.com/nexus-book">http://books.sonatype.com/nexus-book</ulink>
  weekly for any updates to the content.</para>

  <para>If you would like to receive updates whenever there is a change to
  this book, you can subscribe to our Book Announcement mailing list. To
  subscribe to this mailing list, send an email to: <ulink
  url="mailto:book-notify-subscribe@sonatype.org">book-notify-subscribe@sonatype.org</ulink></para>

  <para>We welcome your feedback, please do not hesitate to contact the
  Sonatype team with any questions or ideas you may have about the product.
  We're focused on making the adoption of Nexus Open Source and Nexus
  Professional painless, and we are here to do anything we can to help speed
  up the learning curve associated with some of the more advanced and powerful
  features of Nexus.</para>

  <para>If you have any feedback or questions, you are encouraged to post an
  item in our Get Satisfaction page for this book: <ulink
  url="http://www.getsatisfaction.com/sonatype/products/sonatype_repository_management_with_nexus">http://www.getsatisfaction.com/sonatype/products/sonatype_repository_management_with_nexus</ulink>.</para>

  <para>Tim O'Brien, Sonatype</para>

  <para>${release.month}, ${copyright.year}</para>

  <para>Edition: ${project.version}</para>

  <section>
    <title>Changes in Edition 2.9</title>

    <para>The following changes were made in 2.9:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Added a new appendix: <xref linkend="appendix-contribute" />.
        This chapter provides some of the basic information would be required
        by someone looking to participate in the book project including
        information about the tools used to write the book, how to clone the
        Git repository, and how to execute the Maven build for this book.
        (NXBOOK-557 and NXBOOK-556)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The book now contains instructions for people who want to
        subscribe to the book announcement mailing list. (NXBOOK-555)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Update the Nexus Open Source license to the AGPL in <xref
        linkend="install" /> and <xref linkend="intro" />. (NXBOOK-562)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Updated the Book's copyright to 2011. (NXBOOK-537)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</preface>
