<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="foreword">
  <title>Foreword: ${project.version}</title>

  <para>This book covers both Nexus Open Source and Nexus Professional, a
  product which brings full control and visibility to organizations which
  depend on Maven repositories to manage releases and distribute software. You
  are encouraged to check <ulink
  url="http://books.sonatype.com/nexus-book">http://books.sonatype.com/nexus-book</ulink>
  weekly for any updates to the content. If you would like to receive updates
  whenever there is a change to this user's manual, please send a quick note
  to <ulink url="mailto: support@sonatype.com">support@sonatype.com</ulink>,
  and we will gladly add your email to the update notification list.</para>

  <para>We welcome your feedback, please do not hesitate to contact the
  Sonatype team with any questions or ideas you may have about the product.
  We're focused on making the adoption of Nexus Open Source and Nexus
  Professional painless, and we are here to do anything we can to help speed
  up the learning curve associated with some of the more advanced and powerful
  features of Nexus.</para>

  <para>If you have any feedback or questions, you are encouraged to post an
  item in our Get Satisfaction page for this book: <ulink
  url="http://www.getsatisfaction.com/sonatype/products/sonatype_repository_management_with_nexus">http://www.getsatisfaction.com/sonatype/products/sonatype_repository_management_with_nexus</ulink>.</para>

  <para>Tim O'Brien, Sonatype</para>

  <para>December 26, 2009</para>

  <para>Edition: ${project.version}</para>

  <section>
    <title>Changes in Edition 2.0.1</title>

    <para>The following changes were introduced in Edition 2.0.1 on December
    26, 2009:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Removed HelloWorldPlexusResource from the rest subpackage in the
        list of files generated by the Nexus Plugin archetype. (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-399">NXBOOK-399</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added a section to the Nexus Plugin archetype section about
        changes the target version of Nexus: <xref
        linkend="plugdev-sect-target-version" />. (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-398">NXBOOK-398</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Corrected the plugin descriptor that was listed in <xref
        linkend="plugdev-sect-plugin-descriptor" />. (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-396">NXBOOK-396</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added a section about building the Nexus plugin project
        generated by the Nexus Plugin archetype. (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-397">NXBOOK-397</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changes in Edition 2.0</title>

    <para>The following changes were introduced in Edition 2.0 on December 23,
    2009:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Fixed a problem in <xref linkend="plugins-sect-install" />. This
        section was pointing people at the wrong directory for Nexus plugin
        installation. Fixed a related bug in <xref
        linkend="user-account-sect-installation" /> and in <xref
        linkend="crowd-sect-installation" />. (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-394">NXBOOK-394</ulink>
        and <ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-374">NXBOOK-374</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Separated introduction and explanation of repository management
        concepts into a separate chapter: <xref linkend="repoman" />. This
        change was made because the introduction was becoming too large to
        accomodate more straightforward material explaining Nexus. (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-395">NXBOOK-395</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Rewrote the introduction to focus on Sonatype Nexus.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added sections to the introduction which list the licenses for
        Nexus Open Source and Nexus Professional. This was necessary because a
        few readers had thought that the Creative Commons license on the book
        was applying to all of Nexus. (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-379">NXBOOK-379</ulink>)
        This isn't the case:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The book is Creative Commons NC-ND-BY.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Open Source is GPLv3.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Indexer is EPLv1.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Nexus Professional is available under a commercial
            license.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added the feature matrix comparing Nexus Open Source to Nexus
        Professional to the introduction. (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-369">NXBOOK-369</ulink>
        and <ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-368">NXBOOK-368</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Updated the version of the Nexus Plugin Archetype from
        1.0-SNAPSHOT to 1.2 in <xref linkend="plugdev-sect-archetype" />.
        (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-375">NXBOOK-375</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</preface>
