<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.sonatype.com/tmp/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<preface id="foreword">
  <title>Foreword: ${project.version}</title>

  <para>This book covers both Nexus Open Source and Nexus Professional, a
  product which brings full control and visibility to organizations which
  depend on Maven repositories to manage releases and distribute software. You
  are encouraged to check <ulink
  url="http://books.sonatype.com/nexus-book">http://books.sonatype.com/nexus-book</ulink>
  weekly for any updates to the content. If you would like to receive updates
  whenever there is a change to this user's manual, please send a quick note
  to <ulink url="mailto: support@sonatype.com">support@sonatype.com</ulink>,
  and we will gladly add your email to the update notification list.</para>

  <para>We welcome your feedback, please do not hesitate to contact the
  Sonatype team with any questions or ideas you may have about the product.
  We're focused on making the adoption of Nexus Open Source and Nexus
  Professional painless, and we are here to do anything we can to help speed
  up the learning curve associated with some of the more advanced and powerful
  features of Nexus.</para>

  <para>If you have any feedback or questions, you are encouraged to post an
  item in our Get Satisfaction page for this book: <ulink
  url="http://www.getsatisfaction.com/sonatype/products/sonatype_repository_management_with_nexus">http://www.getsatisfaction.com/sonatype/products/sonatype_repository_management_with_nexus</ulink>.</para>

  <para>Tim O'Brien, Sonatype</para>

  <para>May, 2010</para>

  <para>Edition: ${project.version}</para>

  <section>
    <title>Changes in Edition 2.4</title>

    <para>The following changes were introduced in Edition 2.4 in May,
    2010:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A new epub format was added to the Nexus Book.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Special thanks to Brian Jackson for taking the initiative to fork
    the Nexus book's git repository and add epub support for this book. In the
    process of adding epub support for this book, Brian also contributed some
    fixes to the <ulink
    url="http://code.google.com/p/docbkx-tools/">docbkx-maven-plugin</ulink>.
    Special thanks to Keith Falhgren and Liza Daly of <ulink
    url="http://threepress.org/">Threepress Consulting, Inc.</ulink> for
    providing solid epub support in the DocBook XSL project. </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changes in Edition 2.3.1</title>

    <para>The following changes were introduced in Edition 2.3.1 in May,
    2010:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Fixed incorrect name of the Nexus OSS War file. File was
        incorrectly listed as nexus-oss-webapp-1.6.0.war. Correct name is
        nexus-webapp-1.6.0.war.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Changes in Edition 2.3.1</title>

    <para>The following changes were introduced in Edition 2.3.1 in May,
    2010:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Fixed incorrect name of the Nexus OSS War file.   File was incorrectly listed as nexus-oss-webapp-1.6.0.war.  Correct name is nexus-webapp-1.6.0.war.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Changes in Edition 2.3</title>

    <para>The following changes were introduced in Edition 2.3 in April,
    2010:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Fixed incorrect location of the wrapper.conf in <xref
        linkend="install-sect-startup-scripts" />. (<ulink
        url="install">NXBOOK-462</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Fixed capitalization of sAMAccountName in <xref
        linkend="tbl-ldap-ad-user-element" />. (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-461">NXBOOK-461</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Added a warning about multidomain forests in <xref
        linkend="ldap-sect-mapping-active-directory" />. (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-459">NXBOOK-459</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref linkend="staging-sect-running-nexus-plugin" /> listed
        staging-finish instead of staging-close in the Nexus Maven plugin.
        (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-458">NXBOOK-458</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><xref linkend="maven-sect-custom-for-missing" /> referenced a
        dated version of the Apache Shindig project. (<ulink
        url="https://issues.sonatype.org/browse/NXBOOK-457">NXBOOK-457</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Thanks to Michael Osipov for contributing to the quality of the LDAP
    chapter. Thanks for David Pilato for reporting an error in the
    Installation chapter. Thanks to Joseph Mitchell for reporting the
    staging-finish error in the Staging chapter. Thanks to Ruslan Khafizov for
    reporting an error in the Maven configuration chapter.</para>
  </section>
</preface>
